<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The divine portrait. Or, A true and liuely representation of the blessed sacrament of the Lords Supper: with our due preparation how to receive the same worthily. / Delivered in a sermon, at the Reformed Church of Paris (on Easter day last:) by Monsieur Iohn Mestrezat ... ; Englished by John Reynolds.</title>
            <author>Mestrezat, Jean, 1592-1657.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1631</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 131 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 123 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B00431</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17845</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S94173</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">44920371</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 44920371</idno>
            <idno type="VID">173817</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B00431)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 173817)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2099:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The divine portrait. Or, A true and liuely representation of the blessed sacrament of the Lords Supper: with our due preparation how to receive the same worthily. / Delivered in a sermon, at the Reformed Church of Paris (on Easter day last:) by Monsieur Iohn Mestrezat ... ; Englished by John Reynolds.</title>
                  <author>Mestrezat, Jean, 1592-1657.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[64], 147 [i.e. 174] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A.M. for G. Baker, and are to sold at his shop neere Charing-crosse.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1631.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-K¹².</note>
                  <note>Errors in paging: p. 5-6 repeated in numbering; last p. numbered 147 [should be 174].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Dr. Williams's Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Luke XXII, 19 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:173817:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173817:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE DIVINE POVRTRAIT. <hi>OR,</hi> A true and liuely Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation of the bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Lords Supper: with our due Preparation how to receiue the ſame worthily. Delivered in a Sermon, at the Reformed Church of <hi>Paris</hi> (on Eaſter day laſt:) By
<hi>Monſieur Iohn Meſtrezat,</hi> Miniſter of the Word of God there: Vpon theſe words of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, <hi>This is my Body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Engliſhed by <hi>John Reynolds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>A. M.</hi> for <hi>G. Baker,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop neere Charing-croſſe. 1631.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:173817:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173817:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, Moſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, and Vertuous Lady, MARIE, Counteſſe of DORSET, Gouerneſſe to our High and Hopefull young Lord, and Maſter, Prince <hi>Charles.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAME,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">K</seg>Novving, and conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, that your <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,</hi> (as a ſanctified <pb facs="tcp:173817:3"/>veſſell of <hi>Pietie,</hi> and as another
<hi>Elect La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die</hi>) ſpendes the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt part of your time, and of your Selfe, in Prayer, and in the ſweet and ſacred calmes of Heavenly Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and Contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; And that you make, and eſteeme the firſt to bee, (as indeed it is) your chiefeſt <hi>Ioy;</hi> the ſecond, your grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt <hi>Delight,</hi> and both <pb facs="tcp:173817:3"/>of them your divineſt
<hi>Ambition,</hi> and <hi>Feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie</hi> heere on Earth. I therefore (according to the dignitie of your merits, and the qualitie of my duetie) doe heere embolden my ſelfe, moſt humbly to preſent, and Dedicate to your
<hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,</hi> a ſmall Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation of mine from <hi>French,</hi> Of a
<hi>Sermon</hi> lately delivered (by a worthie Servant of the <pb facs="tcp:173817:4"/>Lord) in the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Church of <hi>Paris,</hi> vpon the firmeſt poynt of our
<hi>Faith,</hi> and the greateſt, and moſt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Myſterie of our Salvation, <hi>The Lords moſt bleſſed Supper;</hi> And if my affection to the <hi>Authour</hi> thereof, doe not deceiue my iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, He hath drawen this
<hi>Divine Pourtrait</hi> of that bleſſed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſo divinely, and
<pb facs="tcp:173817:4"/>ſo artificially and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly depaynted it at life, according to the ſacred <hi>Will</hi> and <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament</hi> of the Great and Heavenly Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour thereof, Our Lord and Saviour <hi>CHRIST IESVS;</hi> as I both hope with confidence, and preſume with ſafetie, that your Honour will receiue it graciouſly, behold it affectionate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and loue and che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh <pb facs="tcp:173817:5"/>it religiouſly; and (conſequently) that all other
<hi>Readers</hi> will doe the like, by the power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Influence of your
<hi>Honourable</hi> Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and pious Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample.</p>
            <p>And in regard, that your conſtant <hi>Pietie,</hi> and inflamed
<hi>Zeale</hi> towards <hi>God,</hi> (as the <hi>Queene</hi> of all your o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther relucent <hi>Vertues</hi>) generally makes you to <pb facs="tcp:173817:5"/>bee, rather admyred, then imitated of the beſt and Nobleſt La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes of <hi>Great BRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TAINE;</hi> Therefore (neither to flatter your <hi>Honour,</hi> or to infringe the truth) I confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beleeue, that this <hi>Pietie,</hi> and this
<hi>Zeale</hi> of yours, was the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marie cauſe, which firſt mooved
<hi>God,</hi> to mooue and inspire the heart of our Potent and Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
<pb facs="tcp:173817:6"/>
               <hi>King,</hi> to giue you the Superintenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie over his young Son, our <hi>Prince;</hi> A ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar favour of <hi>God,</hi> a moſt ſpeciall honour of our <hi>Soveraigne</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you, which yet your
<hi>Honour</hi> deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved before deſired, and received before you (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny way) expected, or dreamt thereof; And the which ſo infinitely reioyceth the hearts and <pb facs="tcp:173817:6"/>and ſoules of the most and beſt of all his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, that they try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph in this his <hi>Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties</hi> happie choyce and election of you, and in your <hi>Honourable</hi> and Vertuous Administra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion over this our Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <hi>Faglet;</hi> As fully hoping, and therefore perfectly aſſuring them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, that as you are now made Governeſſe to the firſt Sonne, of <pb facs="tcp:173817:7"/>one of the firſt and greateſt Kings of the world: So that, your Illuſtrious vertues in your ſelfe, your watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full eye over him, and vigilant care of, and for him, will (by <hi>Gods</hi> propitious Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and Aſsiſtance) infallibly crowne his Royall Parents, with true <hi>Content,</hi> and their Kingdomes and Subiects with perfect <pb facs="tcp:173817:7"/>
               <hi>Felicitie,</hi> to ſee this <hi>Princely Bloſſome,</hi> and <hi>Royall Plant,</hi> fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turely flouriſh, and ſprout foorth to be one of the loftyeſt <hi>Cedars</hi> of
<hi>Chriſtendome,</hi> and (next to our Sacred <hi>Soveraigne,</hi> King
<hi>CHARLES</hi> his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,) the greateſt <hi>Champion</hi> of
<hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Goſpell,</hi> and the Trueſt
<hi>Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> of his Heavenly <pb facs="tcp:173817:8"/>
               <hi>Spouſe</hi> the Church.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Madame,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe if wee make <hi>Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi> and
<hi>Religion</hi> the Soule of our life heere on Earth; That wee are therefore aſſured, God will then heereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter infallibly make it the life of our Soules in Heaven; was like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe a ſtrong motive, and a moſt pleaſing and acceptable Inducement to me, to make this <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> 
               <pb facs="tcp:173817:8"/>(or
<hi>Divine Pourtrait of the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Sacrament of the Lords Supper</hi>) to ſpeake <hi>Engliſh;</hi> for that this ſpirituall and celeſtiall Banquet, (gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by our great Lord and Saviour <hi>IESVS CHRIST</hi> to his belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Apostles, and in them to vs, a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his glorious depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and aſcenſion from Earth to Heaven) is <pb facs="tcp:173817:9"/>the very true life and eſſence, yea, the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Food, and ſacred Manna, whereby all faithfull and regenerate <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> are eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally incorporated into <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them A ſweet and ſacred Meditation, for every one to know and contemplate, and alſo moſt infinitely neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie for all, (by a liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Faith) verie often <pb facs="tcp:173817:9"/>and frequently to apply vnto their Conſciences and Soules, becauſe it is a matchleſſe Iewell, and an ineſtimable Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, which includeth all earthly riches, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſeth and containes all Heavenly benefits and felicities in it.</p>
            <p>Neither am I, or ſo Ignorant, or ſo Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous, to direct this <hi>Sermon</hi> of the <hi>Lords Supper</hi> to your <pb facs="tcp:173817:10"/>Honour, out of the leaſt ſhadow of any premedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated intent or purpoſe, thereby to inſtruct, or teach you in this ſacred <hi>Myſterie</hi> of your Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; becauſe contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riwiſe I firmely know, that your Honour is truely able to teach, and infinitely capable to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct others therein: But I did it purpoſely to recreate your <hi>Zeale,</hi> and to foment and che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh <pb facs="tcp:173817:10"/>your <hi>Pietie,</hi> in this your ſolemne Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to receiue that bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Sacrament, now at this approaching, great and ioyfull Feaſt of <hi>Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> and next there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, as an eternall pledge and testimony of my dutie to your <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors</hi> Service. The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ind benefite, which the reading and meditating of this ſmall Booke, may worke in <pb facs="tcp:173817:11"/>your heart and ſoule, I wholly leaue to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine <hi>Providence</hi> and
<hi>Pleaſure</hi> of Almightie God, whom I religiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pray, may ever bleſſe your Honor (and yours) with all true proſperitie and happineſſe in this life, and with all perfect felicity and glory in that to come.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Aprill 2. 1631.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Honours humbleſt ſervant, <hi>Iohn Reynolds.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:173817:11"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173817:12"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173817:12"/>
            <head>THE TRANSLATOR his Preface to the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was with a holy admiration, and a religious and ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified zeale, that the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Prophet King <hi>David</hi> (contemplating on the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of Gods creatures, and meditating on the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminence and dignitie which hee gaue man over them) Cryed out,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 8.4.</note> 
               <hi>O Lord, our God, how excellent is thy <pb facs="tcp:173817:13"/>name in all the world, And what is man, that thou art ſo mindefull of him, and the Sonne of man that thou vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiteſt him.</hi> If <hi>David</hi> (who was a liuely <hi>Type</hi> and <hi>Figure</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi>) were rapt into this ſpirituall extaſie of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration and ioy, when he conſidered of Gods power and providence, in the workes of his creation; How much more infinitly and thankfully ſhould wee poore miſerable ſinners, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce with true admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and admire with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ioy, at the vnſpeakable and incomprehenſible love of God towards mankinde;
<note place="margin">Phil. 2.8. Col. 1.14.</note> In giving vp his onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Sonne <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> to death; yea, to the ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <pb facs="tcp:173817:13"/>death of the <hi>Croſſe</hi> for our redemption, and that he was ſo gracious a God, and ſo mercifull and indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent a Father to vs, that he ſuffered his bleſſed <hi>Sonne</hi> to dye for vs,
<note place="margin">Tit. 2.14.</note> 
               <hi>That hee might redeeme vs from all iniquitie, and purge vs, to be a peculiar people to himſelfe.</hi> For, wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched ſinners that we are; In <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> where our Forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers gained their life, there (by their wilfull diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and tranſgreſſion) they loſt their righteouſnes and we in them; becauſe the foule ſtaine and Leproſie of that their originall ſin, hath ſucceſſively and actually, made vs, their vnfortunate ſeede and poſteritie, guilty both of Death and Hell; and <pb facs="tcp:173817:14"/>there iuſtly adiudged <hi>to haue our Portions with the Devill and his Angels.</hi> But notwithſtanding all this; God (yet) hath beene as mercifull to vs, as we have bene ſinnefull to him; for although wee were loſt in <hi>Adam,</hi> by
<hi>Nature,</hi> yet we are againe, both found and ſaved in <hi>Ieſus Chriſt by grace;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.6.</note> 
               <hi>Who hath given him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a ranſome for all men;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai 53.4,5</note> 
               <hi>Hath borne our infirmities, and carried away our ſinnes and ſorrows, by ſuffering him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to bee wounded for our tranſgreſſions, and broken for our iniquities.</hi> So that it is the preſent ioy of our hearts, and the future happineſſe of our ſoules,
<note place="margin">Eph. 2.4,5.</note> 
               <hi>That God, who is rich in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie,</hi> 
               <pb facs="tcp:173817:14"/>
               <note place="margin">Eph 2.4,5</note> 
               <hi>(through the great loue wherewith he loved vs) when we were dead by our ſins, hath quickned vs together in Ieſus Chriſt, by whoſe grace we are ſaved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to the ende that all true <hi>Chriſtians</hi> ſhould not deſpaire of <hi>Chriſts</hi> promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes vnto them nor ſo much give themſelues over, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the reprobate ſenſe and pleaſures of ſinne, or to the ſugred inſinuations and trecherous temptations of Satan, as any way to doubt of their ſalvation in the <hi>Lord:</hi> Why, this our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Lord &amp; Maſter, <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> (the great Shepheard of his Flocke, and <hi>Saviour</hi> of his people) who by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporating his Divinitie <pb facs="tcp:173817:15"/>with his humanitie) was wholly compoſed of loue &amp; mercy toward them. Hee, I ſay, a litle before his bloody, yet bleſſed death and paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on the Croſſe) was gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly pleaſed, to honour and ſanctifie his Apoſtles, and, in them vs, who are of the true ſeed of <hi>Abraham;</hi> with the holy Sacrament of his moſt bleſſed Supper, as a diuine pledge, and a firme &amp; authenticall confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of his ineſtimable loue towards vs, and of his watchful care and vigilancy for our ſaluation; I meane for the full perfecting and accompliſhing of our glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication in Heaven with God his father:
<note place="margin">Rom 6.4.</note> 
               <hi>That ſin might haue no more domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion <pb facs="tcp:173817:15"/>over ver vs; becauſe we are now no longer vnder the Law, but vnder Grace;</hi> but that by the worthy recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and holy partaking thereof <hi>(In the imitation of Chriſt and his bleſſed A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles)</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.6.</note> 
               <hi>wee might be rayſed vp together with him in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly places.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is therefore not our owne merits, but onely Gods mercies, not our own workes which are ſinfull, but onely the bleſſed death and paſſion of Chriſt Ieſus which is ſacred, that muſt be, both the triumph, and glory of a Chriſtian: And I confeſſe with ioy, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge with Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Conſolation, that this holy Sacrament of his <pb facs="tcp:173817:16"/>moſt bleſſed Supper (wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the bread of his body was broken, and the wine of his blood powred out and ſhed, for the ſinnes of all mankind) is the perfect pledge, the ſacred ſeale, the full ranſome, and the divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt myſterie of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption in Ieſus Chriſt: And that as wee are abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely cleanſed and waſhed from our originall ſinne, by the water of Baptiſme, when wee enter into the State of Grace, in the Church militant heere on earth; That ſo by the blood of this Paſchall Lambe, Chriſt Ieſus (in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his bleſſed Supper) our ſinnes are wholly defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and waſhed away and <pb facs="tcp:173817:16"/>conſequently, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee ſhall enter into the ſtate of glory, in the Church triumphant in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; So that fighting vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the banner of Chriſt his Croſſe, and being ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually armed with theſe two ſacred Sacraments, we may boldly beleeue, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently aſſure our ſelues, that neither Sathan, nor hell ſhall have power to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile againſt vs.</p>
            <p>And here (Chriſtian Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) before I proceed far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in this my Preface to thee; I give thee to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, That I am not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, with what a great world of different opinions and controverſies this our little world of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, <pb facs="tcp:173817:17"/>is perplexed and troubled with, about this bleſſed Sacrament of the Lords Supper, betwixt the Proteſtant, and the Papiſt, &amp; eſpecially about Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation, the Reall Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and communicating in one kind: In ſo much that an infinite number (yea too great a number) of pens, pulpits, and preſſes, are pittifully (becauſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitably) oppreſſed ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with: and that Chriſts bleſſed body in this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (without pietie, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or charity) is daily di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacerated and torne in pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces with theſe contentions, whereas his owne Coate, (or veſture) was without peece or ſeame; So that our <pb facs="tcp:173817:17"/>ſilly ſoules may well feare drowning, when the barke of our weake faith (maſted and rigged with curioſitie) ſayleth in ſo dangerous and turbulent an Ocean, that hath neither bottome nor ſhoare; and which is daily and hourly toſſed, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to be ſplit, and daſhed in peeces, either with the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering waves of levity and inconſtancy, or with the boyſterous winds of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſd malice, or ſcandalous and erronious virulency: without looking vp to the true day-Starre of their hope, Ieſus Chriſt; or to the Sunne of their ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, God; or without ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voring or thinking, ſafely to arrive, and caſt anchor <pb facs="tcp:173817:18"/>in the Cape of good hope; Heaven. O that the ſpirit of Pietie, ſhould (without piety) thus bee conuerted, and transformed into the ſpirit of Contention. And as for mee (who am the meaneſt, and moſt vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie of all Gods Seruants and Children) bingeniouſly confeſſe and acknowledge; that in ſome few languages I have read ſo many of theſe intemperate Contre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies, and vntimely Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, that I am wearie of reading them; And yet ſo, That I rather pitie, then maligne, firſt their Authors for their ſakes, and then them for their Authors ſakes; and my witneſſe is in heaven &amp; in mine own be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, <pb facs="tcp:173817:18"/>that with my heart &amp; ſoule I wiſh, that all theſe vnſpirituall quarells might be compoſed in peace and amitie, and that theſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate diſputes and lynes might terminate in one, and the ſame Centre, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and that their learned Authors, (having their cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity vanquiſhed with the honour and glory of God) as Chriſtian mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, might bee inſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly faſt knit and vnited to their Head, and grand Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, Ieſus Chriſt: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe contention is not the way to heaven, and that God was found in the ſtill and quiet, and not in the whirle and tempeſtuous winds; As alſo that where <pb facs="tcp:173817:19"/>the great Lamps of learning and lights of the Church, contend &amp; fight about mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of faith, that there aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly the weake ones, and the more illiterat Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans doe infinitly ſuffer in this quarell: That therefore (in the name and feare of God) they would pleaſe to take vp, and embrace this ſaying of the bleſſed Apoſtle
<note place="margin">Heb. 12.14</note> 
               <hi>Follow peace with all men, and alſo holyneſſe, without which no man ſhall ſee God:</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to the ſame purpoſe,
<note place="margin">Ephe. 4.15</note> 
               <hi>Let vs fellow the truth in loue, and in all things grow vp in him, who is the Head, (to wit) Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To call our religion in queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is to doubt therof, and to halt betweene two <pb facs="tcp:173817:19"/>opinions in matters of ſaith is <hi>(with the Luke-warme La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odicean)</hi> to be of neither: I know wee are commanded by the Apoſtle, <hi>To make our election ſure, and taught by the Prophet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſh. 4.14.</note> 
               <hi>That the people who doe not vnderſtand ſhall fall.</hi> I likewiſe know, that curioſitie in matters of Faith and Religion is dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, and that for being too curious in prying into the ſacred ſecrets of God, it is a fatall Rocke, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſome excellent iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments have ſuffered Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke wilfully, and a world of weake wits igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly. That Gods vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed myſteries and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes are as ſecret, as ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred, and as occult, and <pb facs="tcp:173817:20"/>abſtruſe, as they are divine, and that wee are poſitively told, and taught by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 40.28.</note> 
               <hi>That there is no ſearching out of Gods vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding;</hi> VVherefore as I envy no man for his religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; ſo (I prayſe and bleſſe my Redeemer) I am not ſo wretchedly inſtructed in piety, as to deny mine to the world: much leſſe to dare to deſemble it to God: It ſhall ſuffice mee; that I had rather beleeue the truth, then quarell with it, and farre ſooner (and with more alacritie and promptitude) to embrace and follow it, then to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend or conteſt againſt it.</p>
            <p>As therefore wee cannot beleeue in God, before wee <pb facs="tcp:173817:20"/>firſt know him; So wee cannot perfectly know this Sacrament of his bleſſed Supper, except we firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve in it, and in the pure truth, and naked vertue and integritie thereof. I am not therefore of the vnion or communion of thoſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catholique Romaniſts, who are carnall, and not ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all eaters of this bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, and who tye their implicite faith onely to the bare letter, not to the true ſenſe, and to the ſight, not to the figure or commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, which this heavenly myſterie infoldeth and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines; VVho can diſpenſe with their conſciences (yea with their ſoules) rather to eat their God, then to obey <pb facs="tcp:173817:21"/>him; and daily to teare his bleſſed body in peeces with them teach, as they doe hourly with their ſinnes; and who rely on their own poore &amp; wretched merits, rather then on Chriſts rich promiſes, or on the ineſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable treaſor of his bleſſed death and paſſion, premiſed and prefigured vnto vs, in the bread and wine of his ſacred Supper: But for my part; I really and confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beleeue, that Chriſts owne words, <hi>Take, eat, and drinke this in remembrance of me;</hi> doth make this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of his holy Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to bee a myſticall, not a corporall, a ſpirituall, and not a carnall ſacrifice.</p>
            <p>But to leave Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie <pb facs="tcp:173817:21"/>and contention, to thoſe who love them, (in and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this divine doctrine of this Sacrament of the Lords Supper) and to come to that which more neerly and narrowly concearnes our edification to Chriſt, and ſanctification by Chriſt; I ioyfully affirme, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verre, That it hath bene a great part and degree of my earthly ſelicity, to have heard many excellent Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and ſeene, and read many comfortable Tracts vpon this ſacred Supper of the Lord, aſwell on this ſide, as beyond the ſeas; and preached and written, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well by the Samts of God abroad, as by our owne Engliſh Saints and Seruants <pb facs="tcp:173817:22"/>of the Lord here at hom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> who have moſt painful<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> and induſtriouſly travell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> heerein, with much tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> glory to God, with infini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> prayſe and honour to the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> ſelues; and with a world o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> conſolation and happineſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> to their Chriſtian Auditor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and Readers; have piouſly chalked them out the tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and ſafe way to Heaven, and moſt divinely pointed and ſhewed them the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous path-way, and glorious narrow way to God.</p>
            <p>And now (by Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence and mercy) mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting very lately with a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of that heavenly na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, preached (on Eaſter day laſt) to the famous and flouriſhing aſſembly of the <pb facs="tcp:173817:22"/>Proteſtants in the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mned Church of <hi>Paris,</hi> (at <hi>Charenton</hi>) vpon theſe words of our Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour (in the bleſſed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his laſt Supper)
<hi>This is my body:</hi> By the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and reverend Seruant of the Lord,
<hi>Monſieur Iohn Meſtrezat,</hi> the firſt Paſtor and miniſter of that great, and godly congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the worthy Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor of that famous di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, <hi>Monſr. P. Du. Mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lins,</hi> the great light of his time, and Ornament of his Church. I ſay, I no ſooner ſeriouſly peruſed and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly conſidered it; but finding it to bee pend in an elegant &amp; excellent phraſe, and digeſted and caſt into <pb facs="tcp:173817:23"/>a moſt ſpirituall order a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> method; at laſt (after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhort parlie with my ſoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> and a little reluctation wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> my reſolutions) God n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> only ſuggeſted, but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded me to teach it to ſpea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Engliſh, and eſpecially fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> theſe two reaſons, and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſiderations.</p>
            <p n="1">I. That the tranſlatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thereof, infinitly tended t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Gods honour and glory, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> being a perfect and a pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſing way to draw many ſoules to God, aſwell by their ſeeing and knowing of it, as by practiſing and putting into execution, that ſacred diſcipline, and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which it containes.</p>
            <p n="2">II For that the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor and Preacher of it, is <pb facs="tcp:173817:23"/>ſo worthy a Miniſter of Gods word, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> wiſhed and counſelled his beloved <hi>titus</hi> to bee, (to wit)
<note place="margin">Titus. 2.7.</note> 
               <hi>That his life is a Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne and example of good workes, and of vncorrupt doctrine, gravitie, and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritie;</hi> for to my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge (as alſo to all others, who know him, or his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments and abilities) he is ſo learned, and of ſo meeke, and Saint-like a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation, that it is a diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table queſtion, whether his doctrine doe more crowne, and grace his life, or his life his doctrine: And that thorefore it might well ſtand with Gods pleaſure (as it doth referre, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to his honour) that <pb facs="tcp:173817:24"/>the reading heereof might refreſh, and profit ſome Chriſtians heere in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> as well as the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereof hath done ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in <hi>France.</hi> As alſo, that as (at my reſidence in <hi>Paris</hi>) I have taken ſingular de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light and comfort to have often heard him preach, ſo conſequently that others might doe the like here, by viſibly reading, or tacitly ſeeing, and hearing him preach in this his Sermon, <hi>(or Divine Pourtrait)</hi> which ſo lively (yea ſo tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at life) repreſenteth the Sacrament of the Lords bleſſed Supper vnto vs, I being as confident of this truth, as of this preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; That as in moſt of <pb facs="tcp:173817:24"/>his Sermons hee excelleth and ſurpaſſeth others, ſo in this; that hee hath infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitly both ſurpaſſed and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celd himſelfe.</p>
            <p>And although <hi>(Chriſtian Reader)</hi> I have formerly in this my Preface, expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and ſignified to thee, that this little, (yet moſt excellent) Sermon of his doth moſt ſweetly ſhew thee, the ſure, the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous way to heaven and to God, and with a happines (peraduenture) beyond ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, hath moſt fully performed, and moſt diuine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acted thee that part, (whereunto I will referre and commend thee in the Lord) Yet becauſe I am an humble Seruant to Chriſt <pb facs="tcp:173817:25"/>(both in my deſires and affections) aſwell as I am the ſhaddow, and Echo of my Author in this my tranſlation: Therefore I truſt in the goodneſſe of God, and hope in the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritie of mine owne heart, that I ſhall rather right thee, then any way wrong him, in preſuming poorly to gleane after his rich har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt, by aduenturing to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and give thee a word or two of ſpirituall aduice and directions of mine owne, vpon the receiuing of this bleſſed Sacrament of the Lords Supper, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I commend this <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Pourtrait</hi> thereof to thee, thee to it, and you both vnto God.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:173817:25"/>When therefore thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolueſt
<note place="margin">Iam. 4.8.</note> 
               <hi>to draw neere vnto God, that God may draw neer vnto thee,</hi> by receiving and partaking of this his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Sacrament, Thou muſt (in the innocency of thy heart, and the purity of thy ſoule)
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.6.</note> 
               <hi>firſt humble thy ſelfe vnder the mighty hand of God, that hee may exalt thee.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iam. 4.10.</note> 
               <hi>And caſt thy ſelfe downe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, that hee may lift thee vp.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.34.</note> 
               <hi>Thou muſt awake to live righteouſly, and reſolue to ſinne no more;</hi> but hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth to become a new man, and a new Chriſtian:
<note place="margin">Gal. 3.24.</note> 
               <hi>for they that are Chriſts, have crucified the fleſh with the luſts thereof. Thou muſt ſet thy affections on things which are above, and not on things <pb facs="tcp:173817:26"/>which are on the Earth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3.20.</note> 
               <hi>An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thy conuerſation muſt bee i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> heaven, from whence tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> muſt expect thy Sauiour, eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Lord Ieſus Chriſt;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5.25,</note> 
               <hi>Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> if thou live in the ſpirit, tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> muſt alſo walke in the ſpirit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 4.4,</note> 
               <hi>Thou muſt tremble, but n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> ſinne, and thou muſt examin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thy ſelfe vpon thy bed:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 68.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God will try thee, as ſiluer i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tryed:</hi> Thou muſt not de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceive thy ſelfe,
<note place="margin">Galat. 6.7.</note> 
               <hi>for God wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not bee mocked.</hi> Thou muſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not be hot in thy ſinnes, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cold and frozen in thy de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>votion and piety toward<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God, neither muſt thou ſeeme now to bee that in thy humility and zeale, which thou art not: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Hypocriſie towards God, proves treacherie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <pb facs="tcp:173817:26"/>our owne ſoules: But runne thou a Contrary Courſe with thy heart and ſoule, at thy receiving of this great act of thy Salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, this bleſſed Sacrament; for bee thou the death of thy ſinnes, and then God will aſſuredly be the life of thy Soule.</p>
            <p>As for thoſe who either vnworthily receiue, or careleſly deferre, or wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contemne the receiving of this bleſſed Sacrament, they doe aſſuredly ſpin out the webbe of their owne damnation, and ſo being dead in the Lethargie of their owne ſecuritie and prophaneſſe, they hood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wincked ride poſt to Hell: Conſider and remember <pb facs="tcp:173817:27"/>with thy ſelfe,
<note place="margin">Ioel. 1.15.</note> 
               <hi>That the day of the Lord is at hand.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.10</note> 
               <hi>And that death and deſtruction comes from the Lord, as a Thiefe in the night:</hi> That death (the grimme Purſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, and Sergeant of the Lord) d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th neither ſpare nor pardon any ſexe or age, but with his fatall Dart, and Mace (without reſpect or difference) areſteth as well the King as the begger, the Prieſt as the people, and the young as the old.</p>
            <p>Wee muſt not therefore put farre from vs the evill day,
<note place="margin">Amos. 6.3,4,5.</note> 
               <hi>nor ſtretch our ſelues on our beds of Ivorie, nor ſing to the ſound of the Violl,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Prophet meanes all exceſſe of riot, and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth all degree of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcene <pb facs="tcp:173817:27"/>pleaſures, and beaſtly voluptuouſneſſe: For if we love God, we muſt honour him, and if we will honour him, wee muſt loue him,
<note place="margin">Amos 6.3,4,5.</note> 
               <hi>And not wearie him with our ſinnes, nor preſſe him downe with their burthen, as a Cart is with Sheafes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſider wee againe, That as there is but one way forvs to come into the world, ſo that there are a thouſand waies to go out of it. That we are ſubiect to as many diſeaſes as ſinnes; yea, and that diſeaſes doe as fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, and as inſenſibly ſteale into our bodyes, as ſinnes doe into our ſoules; That wee are never neerer death, then when we think our ſelues fartheſt from it, <pb facs="tcp:173817:28"/>and that when we ſuppoſe our ſelues to be ſtrongeſt in <hi>Nature,</hi> wee commonly are then weakeſt in <hi>Grace:</hi> As alſo, that a theeuiſh
<hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtume,</hi> a poore <hi>Apoplexie,</hi> a Cut-throat Squinancy, or a fierce and furious viſitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Peſtilence,</hi> doth many times (in a moment of time) violently ſnatch vs away from the world, and the world from vs, yea, and which is more to be admired, though no leſſe to bee pittied, That ſome times, in the very twinck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of an Eye, we are choa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with a Fly, a Kernell of an apple, a crumm of bread, or a ſmall Fiſh bone; Or elſe have our braynes daſhd out with a fall, either from <pb facs="tcp:173817:28"/>a Horſe, or a ſtaire. O (ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) how ſeriouſly ought we to ponder in our hearts, and how maturely and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly to conſider in our ſoules, how extreame dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous it is for vs, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craſtinate, and deferre: and (conſequently) how infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely neceſſary, &amp; expedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t it is for vs frequently to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue this bleſſed Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the Lords Supper.</p>
            <p>Conſider wee further,
<note place="margin">Iam 4.14.</note> 
               <hi>That wee cannot tell what ſhall betyde vs to morrow, for that our life is but a <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>apour, that appeareth for a ſmal time, and then vaniſheth away.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.24</note> 
               <hi>That all fleſh is graſſe, and all the glory of man, is as the flower of graſſe, and that the graſſe withereth, &amp; the flower <pb facs="tcp:173817:29"/>thereof falleth away,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 13.14.</note> 
               <hi>That we haue no abiding Citie heere, but muſt therefore ſeeke one to come, which is aboue: That as the tree falleth it lyes.</hi> That there is no ſorrowing for our ſins in the grave, and that after our death, there is no place nor hope left vs for a ſecond repentance:
<note place="margin">Heb. 10 31</note> 
               <hi>And that it is a feare full thing to fall into the hands of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Armed in this manner with a lively faith towards God, and with periect love and Charity towards our neighbour, and having freed and cleared thoſe ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſpots of our hearts, and reformed and cleanſed thoſe foule affections and imperfections of our ſoules <pb facs="tcp:173817:29"/>by our (vnfeigned) godly repentance and ſorow; And having now aſſumed and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vp a firme reſolution, <hi>ever hereafter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 5.10.</note> 
               <hi>to approve and doe that which is pleaſing to the Lord;</hi> And contracted a ſolemne Covenant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene God and our ſouls,
<note place="margin">Eph. 5.11.</note> 
               <hi>never any more to have any fellowſhip with the workes of darkeneſſe, but reprove them,</hi> and not henceforth to dare to looke back (with affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) on our forepaſt, deereſt and darling ſinnes, but with infinite hatred &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation of them. Then, I ſay, let vs follow the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of the Apoſtle.
<note place="margin">Heb. 4.16.</note> 
               <hi>Let vs goe vp boldly to the Throne of Grace, that wee may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive mercy.</hi> Let vs goe <pb facs="tcp:173817:30"/>boldly to this table; to this pretious banket of the Lords bleſſed Supper, and eat that ſacred bread of his body, and drinke that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly wine of his blood, in a ſtrong Confidence and Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>memoration, <hi>That Chriſt dyed for vs on the Altar of the Croſſe,</hi> and for the free reconciliation, and full ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, and redemption of our ſinnes.</p>
            <p>And having thus filled our hearts with ſacred Ioy, and repleniſhed our ſoules with ſpirituall and heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gladneſſe, by receining of this moſt bleſſed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, we muſt then have an infinite watchfull eye over our hearts, and place a moſt ſtrong and religious guard <pb facs="tcp:173817:30"/>over our ſoules, that wee doe not hencefoorth once preſume to hearken to ſin, or ſo much as give way, or dare to conſent to looke, or liſten after the treacherous lures and temptations of the world, the fleſh or the devill; and ſo to fall backe into a ſpirituall relapſe of ſinne, which is ten thouſand times worſe, and infinitly more dangerous and perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious then that of any Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall diſeaſe whatſoever, For it is a wofull, yea a wretched miſery, which leaues vs no hope of better fortunes, nor place for worſe,
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.22</note> 
               <hi>If with the Dogge wee returne to our owne vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, and with the Sow, that wee againe wallow in the fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie <pb facs="tcp:173817:31"/>mire of our former beaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſinnes and tranſgreſſions,</hi> For then our end will bee farre worſe then our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning,
<note place="margin">Hoſ 4.7.</note> 
               <hi>Then God will change our glory into ſhame, And then wee ſhall make our ſelues guilty of the body and blood of Chriſt,</hi> (which without his all ſaving grace and mercy) is the high way to endleſſe perdition, and the true way to eternall damnation. No, No, farre be ſuch vngodly and rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious thoughts from our hearts, and ſuch vnſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>all treaſon againſt God from our ſoules; And let vs (who are the ſeed of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ham</hi> by nature, and the Sonnes of God by Grace)
<note place="margin">Hoſ. 10.12</note> 
               <hi>ſtill breake vp the fallow <pb facs="tcp:173817:31"/>ground of our hearts with a holy repentance and ſorrow for our ſinnes,</hi> and with a conſtant and inuiolable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution never to ſinne more; and as (therefore) we have received Chriſt Jeſus by faith,

<note place="margin">Colloſ. 2.6.</note> 
               <hi>So let vs walke in him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theſ. 1.11,</note> 
               <hi>and walke worthy of him, who now calles vs to his Kingdome of glory,</hi> and, which is more, who in a ſpirituall Contract,
<note place="margin">Hoſ. 2.19.</note> 
               <hi>hath vnited and maried vs to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in righteouſneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which regard and conſideration, becauſe wee are ſo highly beloued of God, and ſo infinitly hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the name of Chriſtians (wherein wee ought more to inſult, and triumph, then in all things
<pb facs="tcp:173817:32"/>elſe which are vnder Chriſt) Let vs, I ſay, forſake the ſtincking garlicke and vnions of <hi>Egypt,</hi> (I meane our old beaſtly ſinnes and tranſgreſſions) and for ever hencefoorth ſmell to the ſweet Roſes and Lilies of Heaven, (the delectable love, and promiſes of our Saviour Chriſt Ieſus vnto vs) which are ſo ſweetly watred with his pretious blood, and ſo odoriferouſly perfumed, not with fraga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant odors, or coſtly ſpices of <hi>Arabia,</hi> but with the rich myrrh of Gods ſacred mercy, and with the ſweet and pretious frankincenſe of his divine fauour and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving countenande towards vs.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 134.2</note> 
               <hi>Let vs (I ſay) lift vp our <pb facs="tcp:173817:32"/>hands to his holy Sanctuary, &amp; prayſe the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 31.3.</note> 
               <hi>for that he loves vs with an everlaſting love,</hi> and that (by the bleſſed death and paſſion of his Sonne Chriſt)
<note place="margin">Pſal. 68.20</note> 
               <hi>hee is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come our God, and the God that ſaveth vs,</hi> The which, If we religiouſly &amp; conſtantly performe;
<note place="margin">Ier. 31.12.</note> 
               <hi>Then our ſoules ſhall bee as a watred Garden, and wee ſhall know no more ſorrow:</hi> Then wee ſhall be as the
<note place="margin">Hoſ. 14.6.</note> 
               <hi>Dew vnto Iſrael, and God will make vs grow as Lilies, &amp; will faſten our roots as the trees of Lebanon;</hi> Then
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 3.18</note> 
               <hi>wee ſhall ſee God face to face in his Kingdome of glory,</hi> and there (both) live and raigne with him eternally,
<note place="margin">1 Tim 4.8.</note> 
               <hi>And then hee will crowne vs with a Crowne of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe <pb facs="tcp:173817:33"/>which hee hath reſerued and layd vp for his elect, Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and Seruants.</hi> Of which bleſſed number, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, O God, who art our Creator and Reedee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, (for thy promiſe ſake, for thy <hi>Sions</hi> ſake, and for thy <hi>Sonne, Chriſt Ieſus</hi> his ſake) to make vs: <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy Chriſtian Friend, IOHN REYNOLDS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:173817:33"/>
            <head>THE DIVINE POVRTRAIT. <hi>OR,</hi> A TRVE AND liuely Repreſentation of the bleſſed Sacrament of the LORDS SVPPER. With our due Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion how to receiue it <hi>worthily.</hi> Vpon theſe words of our Saviour: <hi>This is my Bodie, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="introduction">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Sacrament of the
<note n="*" place="margin">Euchariſt.</note> 
                  <hi>Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> (becauſe of its excellencie) hath bin, <pb facs="tcp:173817:34"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:173817:34"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:173817:35"/>and is worthily tearmed a Myſterie; for this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament collecteth and gathereth together all that the new Teſtament hath of moſt admirable, and moſt excellent; and diſcovereth vnto vs the Treaſures of Wiſedome and Intelligence, which are hidden in Ieſus Chriſt; And truely, that which men and Angels themſelues have moſt to admire in this new Teſtament, are eſpecially two things: The one is the meanes whereby Saluation hath beene purchaſed, and procured
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:173817:35"/>to poore ſinners; The other the meanes wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by this Saluation being firſt merited, procured and given to them by Ieſus Chriſt, is after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards applyed, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred to them. In the firſt is ſeene the height, and depth, the length, and bredth of Gods mercy, in ſending here below on Earth his onely Sonne in the forme of ſinfull fleſh, and for expoſing him to the ſhamefull death of the Croſſe, for ſinfull Creatures, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyntly therewith is <pb n="4" facs="tcp:173817:36"/>likewiſe ſeene, the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit vertue of Chriſts blood, to redeeme and expiate the ſinnes of the world, and to obtaine eternall life and glory for thoſe who were dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſly ingulphed, and almoſt loſt in the death and miſery thereof: In the ſecond is remarked and ſeene, that by the means of faith &amp; repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, wretched ſinners, are ſo vnited to the Sonne of God, as if they were compoſed of that body, whereof hee is the head, and they the members; and by this <pb n="5" facs="tcp:173817:36"/>Communion are made Partakers of all the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and benefits which Ieſus Chriſt hath deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and purchaſed for them.</p>
               <p>Now this bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Lords holy Supper, which is as viſible as his Sacred written Goſpell, and Divine Teſtament; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth and expoſeth to vs th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe two efficable points and conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. One way the bread broken, and wine filled out, preſenteth to our eyes the firſt: To wit the body of Ieſus <pb n="6" facs="tcp:173817:37"/>Chriſt broken, and his blood ſhed and ſpilt on the Croſſe, for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of mens ſinnes: And on the other part, mans action in taking and eating this bread, and drinking this wine, denoteth and ſheweth vs the interiour action of the ſoule, who being hungry and thirſty, hath iuſtly her recourſe to this body and blood offered vp to God on the Croſſe, and there findes her peace and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie, vniting her ſelfe by faith vnto Ieſus Chriſt, the Head ſpring, <pb n="5" facs="tcp:173817:37"/>and fountaine of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe and life.</p>
               <p>Wherefore one way to contemplate the wonders of God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards vs, and the other, our duties towards him, that hereby wee may partake worthily of this bleſſed Sacrament, It is needleſſe for vs to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the eyes of our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings any far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then to this very ſame Sacrament, which in it ſelfe will furniſh vs with all things needfull and requiſite for the pertinent diſpoſition of our ſoules, in the partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:173817:38"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:173817:38"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:173817:39"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:173817:39"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:173817:40"/>and receiving thereof. But the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is fully compriſed and containd, in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry words wereby our Lord, and Saviour Ieſus Chriſt doth inſtitute it to vs, which were a briefe declaration of his owne vſe and cuſtome; So that, as this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is a ſhort abridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and epitome of the myſterie of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, ſo the words which Ieſus Chriſt hath pronounced therin, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent matter, and the moſt <pb n="7" facs="tcp:173817:40"/>neceſſary meditations of faith, and to give but a word for all, is the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry true
<hi>Epitome</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendium</hi> of all that which Faith ought to contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate and behold in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Wherefore, Since by the Grace of God, wee are heere this day aſſembled, to prepare and diſpoſe our ſelues for the celebration of the Lords holy Supper, Wee have now pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely choſen for our text and meditation the words of Ieſus Chriſt, which hee vſed in that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:173817:41"/>Supper not to ſtay, or make you liſten to points of Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, which at the firſt hearing of the text you may conceive or ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, (which is not ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite for this time and occaſion; wherein wee have more cauſe to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, and reaſon, to fight againſt the obdu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ratneſſe of our owne hearts, againſt our im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitency, diffidencie, preſumption, and the like vices and ſinnes, then againſt our aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries;) But to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and ſhew you what <pb n="9" facs="tcp:173817:41"/>meditations and functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the words of Ieſus Chriſt ſhould produce and propagate in our ſoules, when wee preſent our ſelues to his holy Table to receive this Sacrament. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though (as wee have formerly ſayd) It be not now my intent or mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to treat of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies, yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, wee are obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to deduce and give you the occaſion, and reaſon of theſe words, and to ſhew the cleare and pure ſenſe thereof, thereby to cauſe to ſlide <pb n="10" facs="tcp:173817:42"/>into your hearts, and to diſtill into your ſoules, the holy doctrine and Inſtructions, which they containe: To which end and purpoſe by Gods aſſiſtance we will eſpecially treat &amp; inſiſt on three mayne points and generall heads.
<list>
                     <item>1. The Reaſon and Senſe of theſe words.</item>
                     <item>2. The Meditations which theſe words ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter, and furniſh vs with.</item>
                     <item>3. The Dutie and Functions whereunto they oblige vs.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="point">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:173817:42"/>
               <head>I. Point, or Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Head.</head>
               <p>The words are; <hi>Take eat, this is my body, which is broken for you;</hi> Where firſt we muſt know, why it was that Ieſus Chriſt ſpake of eating, and why hee propoſed this Sacrament vnder the words of Meate, and Drinke. It is not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to alleadge that Ieſus Chriſt did this occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onally, that is to ſay, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee was at Table, as by occaſion he found himſelfe neer a well, and <pb n="12" facs="tcp:173817:43"/>demaunding water to drinke of the <hi>Samaritane</hi> woman; that the ſpake to her of the grace, &amp; effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy of the holy Ghoſt, vnder the names of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and drinke. This anſwere ſufficeth, when wee demaund why Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt ſpeaking to the troopes and multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of people, before hee inſtituted the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> propoſed himſelfe as bread deſcended from Heaven; and his fleſh as meat, which gave ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting and eternall life; For it is cleare and appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant <pb n="13" facs="tcp:173817:43"/>that Ieſus Chriſt ſpake ſo by occaſion, anſwering thoſe troopes and multitudes which asked him for bread, and who followed him for earthly meate, and for this occaſion hee there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore aſſumed the names of thoſe things, to the which hee ſaw them affected: But here, where it concernes and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends of the Inſtitution of the Sacrament, the anſwere drawen and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from the occaſion to bee at Table, is not ſufficient; For we may demaund againe, why
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:173817:44"/>Ieſus Chriſt placed and ſate himſelfe at Table, to inſtitute and celebrate this Sacrament: For an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere whereof, they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge, and propoſe three reaſons.</p>
               <p n="1">I That Ieſus Chriſt ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving already inſtituted Baptiſme vnder the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude of a Birth; It, was likewiſe very fit, and expedient, that hee ſhould inſtitute his holy Supper vnder the ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude of nutriment, or nouriſhment; For if the beginning of Grace, and of ſpirituall life had bin <pb n="15" facs="tcp:173817:44"/>propos'd in the firſt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, by a Birth in compariſon of a tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall life: It was very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite and reaſonable, that the aduancement, and progreſſe of Grace, ſhould by the ſame com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon, be propoſed by a nouriſhment in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Sacrament. As then Ieſus Chriſt had in Baptiſme given water, which is the principall of the generation of corporall things, to bee a figure of the Holy Ghoſt, which is the principall, and efficient cauſe of the regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <pb n="16" facs="tcp:173817:45"/>of our ſoules; So he inſtituted the Sacrament of his bleſſed Supper, by thoſe things from whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce we have and receiue our temporall nouriſhment, to wit, Bread and Wine; thereby to repreſent vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs the life, which our ſoules receiue of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and blood offered on the Croſſe, from whence it followes, that the word of eating is no more meant, or taken of the letter in this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then that of Birth in the Sacrament of Baptiſme, and that hee who thinkes or pretends
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:173817:45"/>to nouriſh himſelf of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, by his bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mouth, commits the ſame errour which <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>codemus</hi> did, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Chriſt ſpake to him of being borne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine,
<note place="margin">Iohn. 3.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Asked, if man, when hee were growen old, could reenter into his mothers bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and be borne anew.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">II. <hi>Reaſon.</hi> That our vnion with Ieſus Chriſt, being the foundation of the appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation which is made and given vs by the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of Chriſt (For the death and paſſion of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:173817:46"/>Chriſt is not applyed or given, but to thoſe who are one, and the ſame body with him; according as it is ſayd, that Ieſus Chriſt is the Saviour of his body,) It is expedient that this vnion ſhould bee repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented vnto vs: But it cannot more perfectly, or lively be repreſented or figured to vs, then by the vnion of meates with our body, Sith there is nothing which nature doth more ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or efficably vnite to our bodies, then meates by our eating thereof. <pb n="19" facs="tcp:173817:46"/>As then by eating, meats doe become our owne proper fleſh and bones, ſo wee are taught, that by the faith and vertue of Chriſts holy Spirit, wee become one with Ieſus Chriſt, and are made fleſh of his fleſh, and bone of his bone: And againe, that as by the vnion of meates we receiue our temporall life, ſo by our vnion with Ieſus Chriſt wee receiue our ſpirituall and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life.</p>
               <p n="3">III <hi>Reaſon.</hi> That Ieſus Chriſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:173817:47"/>would inſtitute his holy Supper, at the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Eaſter, in which Sacrament the Iewes were accuſtomed to eat a Lambe. And indeed Ieſus Chriſt was at the table for the celebration of Eaſter, But at the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, or Paſſeouer of Eaſter, two things were done and performed, firſt there was a Lambe eaten, and after as for a banquet (and this is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified and recited by thoſe who have written <hi>the Iewes Liturgie</hi>) the Father of the family tooke bread, to wit, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leavened
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:173817:47"/>bread, which was held courſe and poore bread, and in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it to every one of his family, which were ſitting at Table, ſaid.
<hi>Take, eat, this is the bread of miſery, which our fathers have eaten in Egypt,</hi> and taking the Cup, bleſſed it with a ſolemne prayer, which done, they ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered thankes to God, for that he had brought and eſtabliſhed them in a Countrey, which abounded with all proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity, and plenty of Bread, and Wine, in Compariſon of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery <pb n="22" facs="tcp:173817:48"/>and dearth, wherin their Fathers had lived in Egypt, As in very deed all beleeued and held, <hi>That the vnleauened Bread, which God had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed and inſtituted for Eaſter,</hi> was a true ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bole and figure, of the bread of miſery and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, which the <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites</hi> had eaten during their captivitie in <hi>Egypt.</hi> Now Chriſt Ieſus, who would not permit or ſuffer that <hi>Iewiſh Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies ſhould any longer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in the Chriſtian Churches;</hi> inſteed of the Paſſeouer or Feaſt of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:173817:48"/>Eaſter, placed and inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted his bleſſed Supper, as hee had formerly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed and introduced, Baptiſme inſteed of Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, leaving in all Chriſtian Churches, none but theſe two fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures and Sacraments in place and ſteed of all that great multitude, which were formerly vnder the old Law. And ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as the ſeruice of the new Teſtament was ſpirituall, It was alſo conuenient and fitting, thoſe few Ceremonies, which Chriſt inſtituted, were likewiſe ſimple and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:173817:49"/>eaſie, as depending and having relation to the Nature and Condition of the Evangelical Law and ſeruice, which is wholly ſpirituall, and heavenly, whereunto theſe Ceremonies were tyed and conioyned; In which regard Ieſus Chriſt in his Supper, tooke no figure of any formerly prepared meat, procured with coſt or care, or which could not be hourly provided, and had, as was the <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chall</hi> Lambe, but tooke ſimplie Bread, and Wine, as in the ſame <pb n="25" facs="tcp:173817:49"/>ſort and manner that in the Sacrament of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, inſteed of the painefull and grievous Circumciſion, hee inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted the eaſie and ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple aſperſion of water.</p>
               <p>Now for that Ieſus Chriſt hath ſubſtituted his bleſſed Supper in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteed of the feaſt of Eaſter: It followes of neceſſitie, that there muſt bee ſome reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance and conformitie of the Lords Supper to the Feaſt of Eaſter, and of the actions of Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtians in receiving the ſame, to the actions of <pb n="26" facs="tcp:173817:50"/>the Iewes in eating of their Paſchall Lambe. But as this great Feaſt and Paſſeover of the Iewes, was a Sacrament and religious myſterie; ſo, notwithſtanding, it was yet more to feed the mind then the body; wherefore wee muſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue and remember, that beſides, yea above the eating of the mouth, there was the eating of the mind, which was a holy and religious me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation, whereby their ſoules ſhould be refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and comforted ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the quality <pb n="27" facs="tcp:173817:50"/>and Condition of the Churches of their time. That which they did eat with their Corporall mouthes, was a Lambe, ſome bitter hearbes, and vnleavened bread; And that which their minds and heart ought to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate on, was the grace and favour, which God had beſtowed on them, in delivering them from the miſerable ſeruitude and ſlavery, wherin their Fore-fathers had lived in <hi>Egypt;</hi> and for bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to enioy the fruits and fatneſſe of the Land of
<hi>Canaan.</hi> So that <pb n="28" facs="tcp:173817:51"/>at the ſame time, which their bodyes did eate; their ſoules likewiſe had their ſpiritall meate and food, and taſted how good and gratious God was to them, by giving them their deliverance. In the ſame manner Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, inſtituting his Bleſſed Supper at Eaſter, propoſed to Chriſtians a double forme of eating; the one of the mouth, which was that of Bread; and the other of the Soule, which was the medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the great good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and mercy of God,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:173817:51"/>whereby Ieſus Chriſt having beene crucified to death for vs, hath victoriouſly and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly delivered vs from all our miſeries.</p>
               <p>Now let vs here re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark &amp; obſerue, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſympathy &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie, wherevnto the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were called at their Paſſeover, (or Feaſt of Eaſter) to the medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion wherin our Saviour Chriſt called Chriſtians in his bleſſed Supper, to reliſh the goodneſſe of God. The Iewes in their Paſſeover, conſidered that by the blood of a <pb n="30" facs="tcp:173817:52"/>Lambe, their Forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were delivered from the deſtroying and perſecuting Sword of the Angell; the ſlayen and immolated Lambe, being the Ranſome of the firſt borne; And in the fraction (or breaking) and eating of the Bread of the <hi>Euchariſt:</hi> wee Chriſtians doe conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, That the body and blood of Ieſus Chriſt, (as of an immaculate Lambe without ſpot or blemiſh) hath beene offered vp to God in Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, and that by this Ranſome wee are deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:173817:52"/>delivered from the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying Sword of the Angell, (to wit) from all the power and malice of Sathan. <hi>As the Apoſtle tels the Corinthians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.7.</note> 
                  <hi>that Chriſt our Paſchall Lambe hath beene ſacrificed vp for vs.</hi> As then the Iewes conſidering the Lambe, meditated and celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the goodneſſe of God, for giving delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to their Forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, by the Ranſome of a Lambe: So wee Chriſtians ſhould feaſt our minds, and refreſh our hearts with the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation of Gods ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar <pb n="32" facs="tcp:173817:53"/>goodneſſe towards vs, which is infinitly greater and more admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, in that hee hath delivered vp his owne, yea his onely Sonne, to death for the Ranſome of wee poore and wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched Sinners, wherein appeares a dilection and loue, which ſurpaſſeth all vnderſtanding, and wherein (faithfull Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of the Lord,) you may apparantly ſee the excellency of your ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage, and benefits above thoſe of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Teſtament: That which they meditated
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:173817:53"/>in their Paſſeover, was a temporall deliverance; That which you medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate in the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, is a deliverance both ſpirituall and eternall: That which they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered for a Ranſome and deliverance, from the Angels Sword of perſecution and peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, was a ſimple ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtriall, and carnall Lambe; But that which you meditate on for your Ranſome in this ſacred Supper, is the proper body of Gods onely Sonne, crucified and ſlayen for your <pb n="34" facs="tcp:173817:54"/>Sinnes. The Ioy and refreſhing which the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites conceived in their hearts and minds by their meditation, was their delight and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment to have beene delivered from <hi>Pharoah,</hi> and to bee brought into the promiſed Land of
<hi>Canaan:</hi> But what is this in Compariſon of the Ioy and refreſhing, which our ſoules con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, to ſee, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template the vnſpeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble goodneſſe of God, whereby you are deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from eternall death, and conducted <pb n="35" facs="tcp:173817:54"/>and brought into a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, and heavenly
<hi>Canaan;</hi> O therefore if thoſe of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> would conſider, how great, how excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, &amp; how inexpreſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, this feeding and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing of our ſoules is by this meditation; They would not then ſay, that wee returne empty from this bleſſed Sacrament; It is then the Church of Chriſt, which hath the true ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and true refreſhing and ſacietie thereof, and there onely it is, where true peace and felicity
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:173817:55"/>is to be found; And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is, that the word of God teacheth vs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ancient Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites, That what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent ſoever they receiued by their Paſſeover, there yet remayned in their memories a degree of ſlavery and ſeruitude,
<note place="margin">Rom. 1.15.</note> whereof they were ſtill afraid, and the Reaſon of it was, that the curſe of the Law, ſtill echoed and reſounded aloud in their eares; and that the promiſes of remiſſion and pardon for their ſinnes, were ſtill concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and obſcured from
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:173817:55"/>them, and the death of Chriſt crucified for the tranſgreſſions of men, was hidden, and over-clouded from them by the vaile of Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies. Whereas heere (O ye faithfull Chriſtians,) Ieſus Chriſt calles you to the publicke Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his death, and of the pardon and remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of your ſinnes, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh and fill your ſoules with peace and felicity; And for which cauſe and reaſon hee ſaith, in Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 6.35.</note> 
                  <hi>Whoſoever comes vnto mee, ſhall not <pb n="38" facs="tcp:173817:56"/>bee hungry, and thoſe who truſt in mee, ſhall not bee dry, or thirſty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And, therefore Ieſus Chriſt taking bread, ſaid, <hi>Take, eat,</hi> and then hee added, thereunto, <hi>This is my Body;</hi> So that which hee came from taking of, and which he held, (to wit) Bread, he ſaid it was his body, A thing which hee then ſpake moſt eaſily, and clearely; For as there was not the ſmaleſt Child among the Iewes, but vnderſtood, when the Father of his family <pb n="39" facs="tcp:173817:56"/>ſaid, <hi>(Take eat, this is the Bread of miſery, which our Fore-fathers, did eat in Egypt)</hi> that this Bread was ſo named and called by the Father of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, becauſe it was a Commemoration of the bread of affliction, which their Fore-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers had eaten in <hi>Egypt,</hi> according as it is ſaid in <hi>Deutr.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 16.3.</note> 
                  <hi>Vnder the Law ſeven dayes thou ſhalt eat vnleavened Bread, which is Bread of affliction, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou didſt haſtily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part and fly away from Egypt:)</hi> So there was none ſo ignorant, or <pb n="40" facs="tcp:173817:57"/>ſimple, but vnderſtood well, That Chriſt ſaid the bread was his body, becauſe hee was the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>memoration therof, and as the vnleavened bread had beene yearly or dayned for a Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall, (or Comemorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) of the miſeries, which the Iſraelites had ſuffered in <hi>Egypt:</hi> That Ieſus Chriſt eſtabliſhed Bread to remaine till the end of the world, the ſigne and Commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of his Body offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red on the Croſſe: which againe was cleare and evident, becauſe
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:173817:57"/>they named the Lambe, which they did eat,
<hi>Paſque,</hi> an Hebrew word which ſignifieth <hi>Paſſeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,</hi> and which every one well vnderſtood in that Language; <hi>Where wilt thou</hi> (ſaid the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles to Ieſus Chriſt)
<note place="margin">Mat. 26.17.</note> 
                  <hi>that wee prepare for thee, the Paſſeover.</hi> The Lambe which they eat was ſo called, becauſe it was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted in Memory and Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>memoration of the Paſſing over of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying Angell from above, and beyond the Iſraelites houſes. And in this ſame ſenſe they <pb n="42" facs="tcp:173817:58"/>eaſily vnderſtood, that the Bread was called the body of Ieſus Chriſt, becauſe it was purpoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſtituted to bee the Remembrance or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memoration of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy offred on the Croſſe, for the ſinnes of the world: Now although this were ſufficiently cleare and palpable of it ſelfe, yet obſerue heer the ſingular bounty, goodneſſe, and wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Ieſus Chriſt, to repell, and prevent the errour which hee foreſaw; In that he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned and added there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto <pb n="43" facs="tcp:173817:58"/>(as Saint <hi>Luke</hi> and Saint
<hi>Paul</hi> affirme it, in expreſſe tearmes; <hi>Doe this in remembrance of me;</hi> Is there not heer then, iuſt cauſe to admire and wonder, that after all this, That Bread ſhould bee vnderſtood by tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation, to be the body of Ieſus Chriſt, and farre different and otherwiſe then by <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, or Commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration;</hi> From whence it neceſſarily reſults and followes; That in the Church of
<hi>Rome,</hi> a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of Bread, is adored for the body, and perſon
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:173817:59"/>of Ieſus Chriſt, The Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament and Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance having beene confounded with that, whereof it is the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and commemora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>So then Chriſt Ieſus ſaid, <hi>This is my Body, This is my blood,</hi> and yet not ſimply ſo, but according as Saint <hi>Luke</hi> tels vs;
<note place="margin">Luc. 22.19.</note> 
                  <hi>Which is given for vs,</hi> and as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> affirmes, <hi>Which is broken for you,</hi> So then Chriſt repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting vs his body, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands thereby, that hee hath beene delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp for vs to the <pb n="45" facs="tcp:173817:59"/>Croſſe, that is to ſay, that hee hath beene bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and ſacrificed, And likewiſe for the Cup, he ſaid, <hi>This is my Blood which is ſhed for you,</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>king in tearmes of the time preſent, and not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for regard of what hee knew ſhould befall him the very next day, in reſpect of the truth thereof; But alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee gave and ren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dred in a preſent figure, that which ſhould bee done on the Croſſe, the fraction of Bread being a true, and lively repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation of the fraction <pb n="46" facs="tcp:173817:60"/>of his body, as a canon of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> acknowledgeth it in theſe words.
<note place="margin">De con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecr. Diſt. 2. Canon Hoc eſt quod.</note> 
                  <hi>The immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>molation of the fleſh of Chriſt, which is done by the Prieſts hands, is tearmed the Paſsion, Death, and crucifiing of Ieſus Chriſt, but not by the truth of the thing but by the ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the myſtery thereof.</hi> From whence, doth clearly reſult and ſtream foorth vnto vs two eſpeciall things; The one, that in the ſame manner, that the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king (or fraction) of bread in the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per <pb n="47" facs="tcp:173817:60"/>is the breaking of Chriſts body. So in the ſame manner the Bread is the body of Chriſt: but the breaking of bread in the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, is the fraction and crucifying of Chriſts body, not by the truth or realitie of the thing, but by the ſignification of the myſterie, And ſo likewiſe, the bread is the body of Ieſus Chriſt, yet not by the truth or realitie of the thing, but by the ſignification of the myſterie.</p>
               <p>The other branch or point, which reſults <pb n="48" facs="tcp:173817:61"/>hereof is, That this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Supper is the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Ieſus Chriſt, not by the truth of the thing, but by the ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the myſterie, and that it is not a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, but a remembrance and commemoration of a Sacrifice; As indeed Chriſt offered vp no ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to God, but brake the bread and gave it to his Diſciples.</p>
               <p>From whence (belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the Lord) you plainely ſee that, to eſteeme and hold the Lords Supper, to bee a reall ſacrifice, wherein
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:173817:61"/>Ieſus Chriſt hath offered himſelfe vp a propitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory Sacrifice for the ſinnes of the living and the dead, Is a humane Inuention; oppoſite and contrary to the Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Ieſus Chriſt, and to the vſe of this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which was ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to ſhew foorth and proclaime his death and paſsion: And likewiſe it is contrary to the onely oblation of the croſſe; the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> affirming to the Hebrewes,
<note place="margin">Heb. 10.10</note> 
                  <hi>That we are ſanctified by the oblation once made, of the body of <pb n="50" facs="tcp:173817:62"/>Ieſus Chriſt, and therefore that there is no more obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for ſinne.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="point">
               <head>II Point, or gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Head.</head>
               <p>Thus much for the ſenſe of Chriſts words. And now faithfull Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, (to whom God hath revealed and made knowen the truth, and puritie of theſe high and ſacred myſteries) come, and meditate on theſe words of the Sonne of God, all which Heaven hath of moſt admirable ſweet, and delitious; <pb n="51" facs="tcp:173817:62"/>And you (godly ſoules) who iuſtly hunger and thirſt for this grace and mercy of the Lord; come you to feed and refreſh your ſelues with the fat of the houſe of God, and to quench your thirſt in the River of his delights: But firſt wee here require two things of you, (that is to ſay) ſome <hi>Meditations,</hi> and then ſome <hi>Functions</hi> of the heart proceeding from theſe meditations, and both which on theſe words, <hi>This is my Body, which is broken for you, This is my Blood, <pb n="52" facs="tcp:173817:63"/>which is ſhed for you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Meditation hath three Points and Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects.
<list>
                     <item>I. The body and blood of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> in theſe words. <hi>My Body, My Blood.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>II. The Oblation of this Body, and of this Blood, in theſe words, <hi>Which is broken, which is ſhed.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>III. The Fruit of this oblation, intimated in theſe words, <hi>Broken For You, Shed For Many, for the remiſsion of Sinnes.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>In the firſt of theſe, when you heare Ieſus
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:173817:63"/>Chriſt propoſing his body, and his blood, the meditation then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of you is, That it being ſo, that we have ſo expos'd our ſelues to the wrath, and ſo incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the indignation and revenge of God, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of our ſinnes, and tranſgreſſions, that the Iuſtice of God muſt bee ſatisfied, &amp; conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that either wee muſt beare Gods wrath and malediction, and ſo for ever ſtoop and faint vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the heavie burthen thereof, or elſe that ſome other thing muſt bee <pb n="54" facs="tcp:173817:64"/>ſubſtituted in our ſteed and place, to ſatisfie the Iuſtice of God; But no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could bee found out in the whole world to bee appointed in the place of man, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily to ſatisfie for his ſinnes. From the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the world, beaſts have beene offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and theſe Sacrifices of beaſts by the ſenſe and feeling, which our conſcience hath ever gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to men of a ſufficient &amp; valable ſatisfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for ſin, have been practiſed in all the whole world: In the old Law, a man <pb n="55" facs="tcp:173817:64"/>came and put his hands on the head of the beaſt which was to bee ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, as putting her in his place and roome, with an intent and hope to diſcharge and transferre his ſinnes on her: but contrariwiſe natural rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſheweth, that that could no way appeaſe or ſatisfie God; For Gods Iuſtice being (of it ſelfe) moſt perfect, can no way content it ſelfe, with a payment or ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, ſo vnequall and imperfect to the Debt, becauſe all the beaſts of the Earth, placed and
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:173817:65"/>numbred vp together, are not equivalent or to bee compared in valew to one man; Heer then, O here, is the Sacrifice (or Victime) after which (without knowing it) all the world ſighed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired, in offering theſe Sacrifices; and this is the Sacrifice, which all others ought to reve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rence and looke on; When therefore you heare Ieſus Chriſt ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<hi>This is my Body,</hi> you muſt figure, and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent him to you, as proffering and offering vp to God his Father, <pb n="57" facs="tcp:173817:65"/>theſe admirable words and ſpeeches, recited by the Apoſtle to the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes;
<note place="margin">Hebr. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou wilt have no Sacrifice, or offering, but thou haſt given and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated mee a body, Thou haſt taken no delight in Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, And then I haue ſaid, heer I am, I come; And in the beginning of the Booke, it is written of mee; that I doe thy will O God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So heer <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> comming to preſent himſelf in the place and ſteed of all theſe Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, which had beene offered vp vnder the Law, and which were <pb n="58" facs="tcp:173817:66"/>daily reiterated &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued, becauſe, as the ſame Apoſtle ſaid in the ſame Chapter,
<note place="margin">Ibid. v. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>That it was impoſsible, that the blood of Buls and Goats ſhould take and waſh away Sinnes;</hi> And therefore (my beloved brethren) obſerue heer, the readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and favour, which the providence of God makes and provides for you, of a moſt conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient and requiſite Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctime and Oblation. When
<hi>Iſaac</hi> was to bee ſacrificed, there was a Ramme found tyed by the Hornes to a buſh, to <pb n="59" facs="tcp:173817:66"/>bee ſacrificed for him; But here, O Sinners, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold in theſe words, <hi>This is my body,</hi> that great Sacrifice and Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, which the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Gods divine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence haue addreſſed, and ſent you: and reioice that heer is the true Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice (or Victime) which comes to aſſiſt and defend you from Gods heauy wrath and Indignation.</p>
               <p>But Ieſus Chriſt, as being ſimply God, could not preſent him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in a Sacrifice for men, for there wanted a <pb n="60" facs="tcp:173817:67"/>humane Sacrifice, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Sinne had beene committed, and perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trated by man, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Saviour Chriſt tels you, <hi>This is my body,</hi> Hee ſaith not, <hi>This I am,</hi> but, <hi>This is my body,</hi> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by purpoſely to conduct and lead you to the myſterie of his Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whereby he is deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended from Heaven, hath taken and aſſumed a carnall body, and is made man for vs, ſo that conioyntly with theſe words, you at one time ſee your great Sacrifice taken from Earth, and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:173817:67"/>yet deſcended from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; Taken from Earth, for it is a body, deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from Heaven, for it is, <hi>My Body,</hi> ſaid our Saviour Ieſus Chriſt; (that is to ſay) of mee true God with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; Heer therefore is the wonder which you ought to meditate on, That nothing being found in all the world, no nor in the infinit mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude and infinitie of all Gods Creatures, which could be capable to bee our ranſome towards God; Then loe: <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> himſelfe, the only <pb n="62" facs="tcp:173817:68"/>Sonne of God, (deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſo low) as he made himſelfe man, and a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to the end, that hee might bee offered vp a Sacrifice for vs: Hee whoſe Eſſence was wholly ſimple, and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, aſſumed a body, and being materiall, and carnall. Hee who was inuiſible to our eyes, hath made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe conſpicuous, and viſible to vs, permitted and ſuffered himſelfe, to be beaten, tyed and nay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to a Croſſe, yea to bee runne thorow with a Speare, and in a word, <pb n="63" facs="tcp:173817:68"/>capable to be ſacrificed. And heer you may know and find, why Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, holding the Bread, ſaid not, <hi>This is my Divinity,</hi> but, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> (That is to ſay) becauſe not his Divine, but onely his Humane nature could bee offered vp in Sacrifice: The Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity is well conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, but ſtill as offering, not as offered, according as the Apoſtle ſaid to the Hebrewes,
<note place="margin">Heb. 9.14.</note> 
                  <hi>That Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt offered himſelfe vp to God, by the eternall Spirit;</hi> By which means, It is not the eternall <pb n="64" facs="tcp:173817:69"/>Spirit which hath beene offered (For that which was offered was to die) But the body hath been offered by the eternall Spirit.</p>
               <p>And here ariſeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs another wonder (to wit) that although Chriſts humane nature be offered, nevertheleſſe it is of as great a price and value, as if his Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity it ſelfe could have beene offered, and the reaſon hereof is, becauſe this his humane nature compoſed not, but one, and the ſame perſon with the divine nature.
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:173817:69"/>For this body which was crucified, was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally vnited to the eternall Spirit; and this miracle or wonder, is given you for your me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation, in that Ieſus Chriſt holding the bread, ſaid not indefinit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> which is broken for you, but <hi>This is my Body,</hi> as if hee ſaid, <hi>This is a humane Bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy, and yet mine;</hi> to the end wee might know that this vivifying, or quickning fleſh, that is to ſay, to bee a worthy Ranſome for the life of the world. Sith it is the <pb n="66" facs="tcp:173817:70"/>fleſh of a man, who is both God and man: In the Leviticall Law <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> ſprinkling of blood, when God contracted Alliance with the <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites,</hi> ſaid, This is the blood of the Teſtament, which God hath ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for you; But this blood was the blood of Beaſts; Now heer in the Sacrament of his Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per is propoſed and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to you the blood of God, according as the Apoſtle ſayth in the
<hi>Actes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Actes 20.28.</note> 
                  <hi>That God hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed the Church, by his blood.</hi> And behold my <pb n="67" facs="tcp:173817:70"/>brethren to what a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of glory of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell caries you in the New Teſtament above his faithfull Seruants of the old: wherefore here revoke to your mind and memory, theſe paſſages of <hi>Pauls Epiſtle to the Galathians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 4.4,5</note> 
                  <hi>God ſent foorth his Sonne made of a Woman, and made vnder the Law,</hi> And writing to the
<hi>Romanes,</hi> againe like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſaid,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.3.</note> 
                  <hi>God ſending his owne Sonne in the Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude of ſinfull fleſh, and for ſinne, condemned ſinne in the fleſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And before were paſſe <pb n="68" facs="tcp:173817:71"/>to the Meditation of the enſuing words, I pray obſerue heere againe with mee in theſe,
<hi>This is my Body,</hi> the cleare re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation of all which Superſtition, and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Inuentions pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of the interceſſion and meditation of Saints, and of their ſuffering for the expiation of the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>emporall paine of our ſinnes; which pretended ſufferings and ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are partly the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, whereof the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> drawes his In<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dulgences, and Pardons, which makes, that the <pb n="69" facs="tcp:173817:71"/>Saints are a peece and part of our Sacrifice; But Ieſus Chriſt hath deſigned it, and the price of our deliverance in theſe words, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> for hee ſaid not,
<hi>This is a part of my Body,</hi> and part of the bodyes of <hi>Saints,</hi> who ſhall ſuffer for you; If our Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries conſider, that the Sacrament of the Lords Supper preſenteth and expoſeth to our eyes, our
<hi>Price,</hi> and <hi>Ranſome</hi> (as ſome of the Ancients for that cauſe and reaſon tearme the Sacrament, our Price, and if they
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:173817:72"/>likewiſe conſider, that this Sacrament propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth not to vs the bodies of men, but the body of Chriſt, they ſhall find that there is no other price for our Ranſome and Redemption, but this body. And although theſe people which ſay, That this Sacrament of the Lords Supper is the Abridgement of the myſteries of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, doe they accuſe it of Imperfection not to have propoſed or given it all our Price and Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, And thoſe who daily make and create <pb n="71" facs="tcp:173817:72"/>the body of Chriſt, and who pretend daily to offer him, wherefore doe they not content themſelues. But heer let them vnderſtand, and hearken to the thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring words of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle writing to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.13.</note> 
                  <hi>Is Christ divided, hath Paul beene crucified for you?</hi> I af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme that the Bread of this holy Supper ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vs alſo a Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the faithfull with Ieſus Chriſt; for as the ſame Apoſtle writes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to the
<hi>Corinthians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.17.</note> 
                  <hi>Wee who are many, are one <pb n="72" facs="tcp:173817:73"/>Bread and one Body;</hi> But it is a Communion with Ieſus Chriſt, <hi>To receive,</hi> and not <hi>To give;</hi> To re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive (I ſay) of Ieſus Chriſt the expiation and remiſſion of our ſinnes, and not to give or conferre it to other mens merits. A Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion to bee freed, bought, and vivified (or quickned) by him, and not to free, buy, and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vifie with him.</p>
               <p>The ſecond Obiect of our Meditation, is the Oblation of this body in theſe words, <hi>Which is broken; This is my Blood
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:173817:73"/>which is ſhed.</hi> In the words, <hi>This is my body;</hi> you have ſeene Chriſt Ieſus made capable to be this Sacrifice, but in theſe latter words, you ſee him actually to be a Sacrifice, and here is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, you, to meditate and contemplate firſt the Immolation, and then the Oblation of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice; The Sacrifice is a ſoveraigne honour gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and yeelded to God, which conſiſts in an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame vnmaking and diſſolution of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which diſſolution and vnmaking, is not nor <pb n="74" facs="tcp:173817:74"/>cannot be extreame, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept by the deſtroying of the thing which is offered; wherefore all things (heretofore) which were offered vp in Sacrifice to God, were firſt to be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; For it is one thing to bee offered ſimply, and another thing to be offered vp in Sacrifice; As for example, The Sacrificators, the <hi>Levites</hi> and the firſt borne of
<hi>Iſrael,</hi> were offered vp to God, But how not offered vp in Sacrifice, becauſe they ſtill remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned living: All things <pb n="75" facs="tcp:173817:74"/>then offered in Sacrifice ought firſ to be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, if they were liquid, or wet things without life, they were to bee ſhed; If ſolide things, without life, they were to be burnt; Or if living things, they were to bee killed, and for witneſſe and Teſtimony of a true death, there muſt needs bee an effuſion of the Beaſts blood, becauſe blood being the ſeat of the Beaſts life, the ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of blood from the fleſh, ſhewed and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured the ſeparation of life from the body, and <pb n="76" facs="tcp:173817:75"/>conſequently an entire death; And in the expia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, and propitiatory Sacrifices this was the more requiſite and need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, for that theſe Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices were ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for typicall and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſinne; But the abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute ſatisfaction and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piation for ſinne, muſt conſiſt in the death and deſtruction of the thing offered; becauſe the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle peremptorily and truely tels vs,
<note place="margin">Rom. 6.33</note> 
                  <hi>That the wages of Sinne, is death,</hi> from whence you firſt ſee wherefore it was, that of neceſſity Chriſt <pb n="77" facs="tcp:173817:75"/>muſt die, For the wages of Sinne being death, it muſt needs follow, that he who placed himſelfe an Vndertaker for Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, muſt vndergoe the puniſhment ordained for Sinne: Secondly from hence you likewiſe ſee, wherefore it was, that the blood of Chriſt was ſhed in his death, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from his body; to wit thereby to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe and ſhew the truth of the death, and expia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Sinne, as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle to the Hebrewes proves by legall figures, that Ieſus Chriſt muſt <pb n="78" facs="tcp:173817:76"/>die, and ſhed his blood in Sacrifice, becauſe ſaith hee,
<note place="margin">Heb. 9.22.</note> 
                  <hi>That according to the Law, all things are purged and purified by blood, and without the effu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of blood there is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion.</hi> So Ieſus Chriſt, by ſhedding his blood, hath accompliſhed the figures of the Law, and given vs this Conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that the Ranſome and expiation of our ſinnes is entire and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. And hence (as it were in paſſing) you learne two things.</p>
               <p n="1">I. That it is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that there is any
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:173817:76"/>propitiatory Sacrifice without blood, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently impoſſible, that the Maſſe, wherein there is neither death, nor effuſion of blood, be a propitiatory Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for ſinnes, as our Aduerſaries call it.</p>
               <p n="2">II In the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, It was needfull that the body and blood of Ieſus Chriſt, was repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to vs diſtinctly and ſeverally, for that there were two ſignes, (to wit) <hi>The Bread bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and the Wine filld out,</hi> which was the Reaſon why Ieſus Chriſt did
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:173817:77"/>not only ſay, <hi>This is my Body broken,</hi> but alſo takes the Cup and ſaid, <hi>This is my blood which is ſhed,</hi> Becauſe without effuſion of blood there could be no remiſſion of ſinne, From whence it followes, That the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and cutting away of the Cup in the Lords Supper (which ſhewes the blood of Chriſt to bee ſeparated from his body) takes away from the myſterie of that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Supper, it's pleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, power, &amp; perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, depriving it of the ſigne of the Condition
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:173817:77"/>requiſite for the expia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſinnes, (to wit) the effuſion of blood.</p>
               <p>But this is told you but curſorily, and as it were in paſſing: Now the chiefe and principall Meditation, which wee require of you in this obiect, is three things.
<list>
                     <item>I. Of Chriſts great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſing, and making him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe as it were nothing.</item>
                     <item>II. Of the horror, and grievouſneſſe of ſinne, as the direct oppoſition of the perfect ſanctity, and abſolute holineſſe of God.</item>
                     <item>III. Of the immenſe <pb n="82" facs="tcp:173817:78"/>love and charity of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt towards vs.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>I ſpeake firſt of Chriſts great debaſing, and eſteeming himſelfe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; For, (if you for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly vnderſtand and remember) Ieſus Chriſt abaſed himſelfe ſo low, as to cloath and incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate himſelfe with our wretched nature, and to make himſelfe after the ſimple ſemblance of men. But here behold him now, hee makes himſelfe leſſe then man, as he ſaith in the <hi>Pſalmes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 22.6.</note> 
                  <hi>I am a Worme, and no man, the ſhame of men, and the <pb n="83" facs="tcp:173817:78"/>contempt of the People:</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold how he makes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a Sacrifice, and aſſumes and takes on him the condition of Beaſts, which were ſlain in the ancient Law for the ſinnes of men; O Lord Ieſus, who can ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently comprehend the depth of this thy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame humiliation, and making thy ſelfe as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, who from the heavenly Throne of thy glory, haſt been placed, in forme of a Victime, vpon the Altar of the Croſſe; And that thou wouldeſt die, yea die a <pb n="84" facs="tcp:173817:79"/>ſhamefull and moſt ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominious death for vs, according as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten,
<note place="margin">Gal. 3.13.</note> 
                  <hi>Curſed is every one, that hangeth on a Tree.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From this, paſſe wee on to the ſecond thing; which is, the Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, of the horrour, grieveouſneſſe, yea and the odiouſneſſe of Sin: For I pray you, how wicked was it in it ſelfe, and how execrable in the eyes of God, that the onely Sonne of God muſt needs ſuffer ſuch grievous paines and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; The Law did well ſhew the odiouſnes <pb n="85" facs="tcp:173817:79"/>and abomination of Sin, by the Sacrifices, and Aſperſions of blood, which it required for the Expiation thereof; But all that is nothing in Compariſon of this which the Goſpell ſhewes vs, becauſe theſe Sacrifices and Aſperſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Law were of Beaſts, and of the blood of Beaſts, but heer it is the onely begotten Son of God, who hath beene given to death, to expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate ſinne, and to cover the foulneſſe and enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie thereof. Behold then, O Sinners, with <pb n="86" facs="tcp:173817:80"/>aſtoniſhment, by the greatneſſe of the ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction; the horrour of this ſinne, and thereby to learne to hate and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt it. Nature, to ſhew how grievous and odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſinne was, ſince the fall of
<hi>Adam,</hi> became harried over with thorns and briars, and changed many of her plants into poyſons; The aire grew thicke with ſtormes, and was many times infect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to puniſh ſinners; The Sea impetuouſly moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted her angry waues and ſurges, and cauſed infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite ſhipwrackes; <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams</hi>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:173817:80"/>owne perſon, (and his poſterity,) ſtrayed from his temper, and by ſickneſſe and diſeaſes had drawen the Empire of death into his owne entrailes and bowels; mans wiſedome was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcured with ignorance, and tormented with ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regular and extravagant paſſions; and all this befell and hapned to the world for ſinne. But now behold, Heaven, (who againſt ſinne, and to the end, and intent to expiate and deſtroy it,) delivers vp to death, that which it had and held <pb n="88" facs="tcp:173817:81"/>deareſt, and to reproach, and ſhame, that which it held and poſſeſt of moſt glorious For here God the Father of heauen ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth his ſweeteſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights to the bitter tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Croſſe. Heere Chriſt Ieſus, his onely beloved Son, who yeeldeth &amp; abandoneth his life, and who to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy ſinne, (ſo extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hee hates it) doth vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily and willingly deſtroy himſelfe. And heere conſidering, and meditating further, how odious ſinne is to God, let vs admire how per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:173817:81"/>Gods iuſtice and ſanctitie is, &amp; let vs ſay, that here it is, where this ſanctitie manifeſteth it ſelfe at full in her brigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Orient; It is in this myſterie, that the <hi>Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phims</hi> crie, <hi>Holy, holy, holy,</hi> the Eternall of Armies: for if he ſhew forth his righteouſnes and ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie here below, in puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing and ruining ſome of his creatures by his iudgements; how much more doth hee manifeſt it by the death of his onely beloved Sonne, to whom ſinne preſented it ſelfe to be puniſhed.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:173817:82"/>Come we now to the third mediation which wee require of you, wherein we may behold the exreame debaſing &amp; annihilating of the Son of God; to ſee the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſe Loue, both of this heauenly Father and Sonne towards vs, for that the Son hath beene ſo grievouſly handled and tormented for vs. What Abyſſus of affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and mercy is this towards man? Is there any minde or ſpirit, though angelical, which cannot bee raviſhed and ſwallowed vp heereat? <pb n="91" facs="tcp:173817:82"/>Prophane Infidells and Atheiſts, who are incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulous of the myſteries of the Chriſtian faith. Know ye, that it ſhewes you the higheſt charity, and perfecteſt ſanctitie, that the heart, or wit of man can poſſibly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d or conceiue. And of God bee a ſoveraigne ſanctitie, an immenſe charity and goodneſſe, (as his being cannot bee but all perfection) know that the new Teſtament ſheweth God to men, and reveales them this vnexpreſſable and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible ſanctity <pb n="92" facs="tcp:173817:83"/>and charity, which is the ſame that Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaid,
<note place="margin">1. Iohn 4.16.</note> 
                  <hi>God is Love, and hee that dwelleth in Love, dwelleth in God and God in him &amp;c.</hi> That God is Charity, and in this is manifeſted his Charity, For that God hath ſent his onely Sonne into the world; to the end that wee live by him, and in this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine is Charity, not that we have loved God, but becauſe hee hath lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved vs, and hath given his Sonne to bee a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiation for our ſinnes. And heer it is, that the new Teſtament, hath <pb n="93" facs="tcp:173817:83"/>many great aduantages and ſingular benefits, and prerogatives above the old one of the Law, Seeing that herein God fully diſcovereth the rich Treaſures of his goodneſſe. In nature we ſee GODS goodneſſe towards man, for that for a time hee enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines and maintaines himſelfe in life by the death of Beaſts, whoſe fleſh ſerues him for food and ſuſtenance; But here God gives and purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to man, an eternall life by the death of his onely Sonne, Here hee <pb n="94" facs="tcp:173817:84"/>gives to man not his Creatures, as in the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, but his onely well beloued Sonne himſelfe; yea and to ſinfull man. Wherefore it is, that the Apoſtle affirmes to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Cor. 3.18.</note> 
                  <hi>We all behold, as in a Mirrour, the glory of the Lord with open face,</hi> and <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> tels vs, <hi>That none having ever ſeene God, it is he that hath revealed him to vs.</hi> Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full brethren in the Lord, open the eyes of your vnderſtandings, and ſee how God manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth himſelfe, and how he makes himſelfe pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pably <pb n="95" facs="tcp:173817:84"/>viſible to you, by this immenſe Love and Charity, which this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> preſenteth and repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth to your eyes. If then on theſe words,
<hi>This is my Body,</hi> you have meditated on the Love, and Charity of Chriſt humbling himſelfe ſo low, as to cloth himſelfe with our weake body and nature, then medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate on this greater de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of Charity, which hath cauſed him to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the forme of a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for vs (which was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready exceeding much, <pb n="96" facs="tcp:173817:85"/>to him who was the Creator, and the King of glory) but alſo to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe himſelfe to death in this forme and ſhape of a Seruant, yea to the ſhamefull death of the Croſſe, which is the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry meditation of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle to the <hi>Philippians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Philip. 2.6,7,8.</note> 
                  <hi>Ieſus Chriſt, being in the forme of God, thought it no robberie to make himſelfe equall to God: But he made himſelfe of no Reputation; and tooke on him the forme of a Seruant, and was made like vnto man, and found in the ſhape of a man, who humbled himſelfe, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came <pb n="97" facs="tcp:173817:85"/>came obedient to death, yea to the death of the Croſſe;</hi> And the ſame Apoſtle, raviſhed in this medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſaith in another place,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.32</note> 
                  <hi>Who ſpared not his owne Sonne for vs, but gaue him for vs all to death;</hi> Hee ſaith not ſimply, that he hath given him, <hi>but that he hath not ſpared him,</hi> as if he ſhould have ſaid, hee made no diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, to expoſe him for vs to extreame paine and torments. A degree of Charity, which the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels themſelues cannot ſufficiently comprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, and therefore the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:173817:86"/>poſtle requireth in vs, the Spirit of wiſedome and revelation, to wit, that the eyes of our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding bee ſo illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 3.13.</note> 
                  <hi>that wee may know, what is the length, breadth, height, and depth of this love of God towards vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In a word, vpon this obiect, let vs briefly col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect and conſider againſt our adverſaries of the Church of Rome, That in this holy Supper and Communion, the body of Ieſus Chriſt is not ſimply propoſed, as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding it to bee a <pb n="99" facs="tcp:173817:86"/>body; nor the blood, as taking it for blood, but the body, as vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it to be broken, and the blood, as taking it to bee ſpilt; Becauſe in that conſiſteth all the merit of our ſalvation, and all the cauſe of our life. From whence it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, That the action wherewith wee receiue the body and blood of Chriſt, cannot chooſe but bee ſpirituall, to wit, an action of the ſoule, and no way of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, becauſe the bodie cannot bee taken as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, broken; nor <pb n="100" facs="tcp:173817:87"/>the blood, as meant ſhed, except by Faith: For thoſe forepaſt, and beti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded things on the croſſe, that is to ſay, the break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the body, and the effuſion of blood, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee giuen or preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the ſoule, but by the meditation of Faith.</p>
               <p>The third obiect of our Meditation, is the fruit and benefit of this obligation which were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by Chriſts body and blood, in theſe words, <hi>Broken for you, Shed for many,</hi> for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinnes. And heere two conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons <pb n="101" facs="tcp:173817:87"/>againe preſent them to vs:
<list>
                     <item>I. Of the perſons, for whome Ieſus Chriſt is offered.</item>
                     <item>II. The profit and benefit which it brings them.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Of the perſons; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, that he offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth himſelfe for wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched and ſinfull crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, who in regard of his excellent being, are nothing but duſt and aſhes: and as it were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med but yeſterday; but, which is more, for crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures infected with ſinne, guilty of rebellion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <pb n="102" facs="tcp:173817:88"/>him, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed enemies of his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine maieſtie, both in their thoughts, and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked workes and actions, which the conſideration of the Apoſtle to the <hi>Coloſsians</hi> thus expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth;
<note place="margin">Col. 1.21.</note> 
                  <hi>You which in times paſt, were ſtrangers and enemies; becauſe your minds were ſet in evill workes; he now alſo hath reconciled, in that body of his fleſh, to make you holy, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blameable, and without fault in his ſight.</hi> And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo writing to the <hi>Romans,</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">Rom. 5.6,7,8.</note> 
                  <hi>For Chriſt, when we were yet of no ſtrength, <pb n="103" facs="tcp:173817:88"/>at his time, dyed for the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly,</hi> adding againe far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>doutbleſſe one will ſcarſe die for a righteous man, but yet for a good man,</hi> but <hi>God ſetteth out his love to vs, ſeeing that whiles we were yet Sinners, Chriſt died for.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The other conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, proceeds from the profit and benefit which it brings vs; and Ieſus Chriſt defines it, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaith, that it is for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſins: And this is the profit and benefit, which to expreſſe the Prophets aleage, <hi>that our ſinnes have beene throwen
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:173817:89"/>into the bottome of the Sea, and that God remembreth them no more, and that as farre diſtant, as the Eaſt is from the Weſt, ſo farre from him, the Lord hath caſt away our ſinnes, and the figures vnder the Law, to wit, that of the Goat Hazazel, teaching, that our ſinnes have beene caried in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a deſert and vnhabitable Countrey, never to returne more in Gods ſight and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence;</hi> Which beleeving, wee ſee all evils, as they are paines and torments, to have loſt their being in the faithfull righteous man; yea and that death <pb n="105" facs="tcp:173817:89"/>it ſelfe is ſwollen vp in victory, and the Law with his curſes, (which were as a contrary obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation) is quite raſed out &amp; defaced by the blood of the Sonne of God, cleare aboliſhed, cancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and faſtened to his Croſſe, as the Apoſtle teacheth to the <hi>Coloſians:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Col. 2.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Likewiſe Sathan, who per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed nothing, but as the Executioner of Gods iuſtice againſt Sinners,</hi> by this alone death found all his power to be vanqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and overthrowen, as the Apoſtle ſheweth vs in the ſame Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:173817:90"/>of the ſame Epiſtle to the <hi>Coloſsians,</hi> in theſe words,
<note place="margin">Col. 2.15.</note> 
                  <hi>Chriſt hath ſpoyled the Principalities and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and hath made a ſhew of them openly, and hath triumphed over them on the Croſſe:</hi> But beſides, that our enemies and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions are taken away and defaced, by this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of Ieſus Chriſt, ſo likewiſe all ſorts of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits and benefits are put in place thereof; as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny promſes as there are; they are ſo many, <hi>Yeas</hi> and
<hi>Amens</hi> in Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus; life is given, which is a new, ſpirituall, and <pb n="107" facs="tcp:173817:90"/>divine life by regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and the new hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Sanctuary is ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto vs,
<note place="margin">Heb. 10.19</note> 
                  <hi>for there wee have leave and liberty to enter by the blood of Chriſt:</hi> and therefore it is
<hi>that the earthly vaile of the Templerent in peeces at his death.</hi> The Kingdome of God is given vnto vs, and wee are made chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and heires, to poſſeſſe and enioy all the goods and treaſures of God, as the Apoſtle ſaith,
<note place="margin">Gal. 4.6,7.</note> 
                  <hi>That Ieſus Chriſt having beene made ſubiect vnder the Law, hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed vs from the Law,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:173817:91"/>to the end, that wee ſhould receive the adoption of children: and that if wee are children, wee are alſo heires of God by Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn 17.11.</note> 
                  <hi>yea God himſelfe is given to vs in his Sonne, to the end, that wee be in him, and he in vs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>and likewiſe that one day, he be all things in all.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="point">
               <head>III. Poynt, or gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Head.</head>
               <p>Theſe are the Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which the words of Ieſus Chriſt in his Supper requireth of vs; And now come wee to ſee the acts &amp; functions, <pb n="109" facs="tcp:173817:91"/>which theſe Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ought to produce in our hearts, the which likewiſe reſult and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend from theſe words of Ieſus Chriſt: Theſe actes and functions are fiue, to wit,
<list>
                     <item>I. The feeling of our miſery, and a godly ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for having ſinned.</item>
                     <item>II. The beliefe and aſſurance of the remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our ſinnes.</item>
                     <item>III. The ſanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſoule, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, of Loue and Charitie towards our neighbour.</item>
                     <item>IIII. Our conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <pb n="110" facs="tcp:173817:92"/>and patience in affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.</item>
                     <item>V. Our hope of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly felicitie.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>I begin with the fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of our miſerie, and a religious or godly ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for having ſinned; that is to ſay, by conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering by the breaking of Chriſts body, which is propoſed and intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to vs in the breaking of bread, the paine and torments which we haue deſerved. For my belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Brethren, it is for vs, that Chriſts body hath been broken with cruell torments on the Croſſe; <pb n="111" facs="tcp:173817:92"/>and therefore this ſad &amp; wofull ſpectacle doth both ſhew and teach vs, that in requitall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, wee haue deſerved to bee bruiſed and broken with torments for ever. Chriſts ſufferings, and groanes vnder the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of Gods wrath, is a pourtrait (or mappe) of that miſerie, wherein we all ſhould haue periſhed for our ſinnes. Behold then, O ſinner, the terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble indignation &amp; curſe of God, which violently was comming to alight and fall vpon thee. Thou who art inſenſible of thy <pb n="112" facs="tcp:173817:93"/>miſery, here behold and ſee thy condition in the eſtate of Ieſus Chriſt on the Croſſe. See, I ſay, thy torments and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; and when thou ſeeſt this Bread in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Supper, bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, ſay: O Lord, here I am, who haue deſerued to bee bruiſed, &amp; broken with the rodde of thine anger. It was I who had ſinned, and therfore me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited to ſupport and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer thy fierce indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; from thence there muſt bee ingendred and borne in our hearts, a holy and a religious ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, <pb n="113" facs="tcp:173817:93"/>for that wee haue bin the efficient and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all cauſe, that the Sonne of God hath ſuffered all theſe vndeſerved tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures &amp; afflictions. Seeſt thou, (O Chriſtian) the body of Ieſus Chriſt broken on the Croſſe? It is therefore requiſite, that thou breake thy heart with ſorrow, for that thy ſinnes haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced all this evill, and cauſed all this calamitie. Therefore behold the drops of blood trickling downe the face of Ieſus Chriſt. Thou who drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt and ſuppeſt vp ſinne <pb n="114" facs="tcp:173817:94"/>as water, loe, thy ſinnes are the ſharpe thornes, which haue pricked and pierced his head. Thee, to whom thy ſinne is ſo ſweet and delicious, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, they are thy ſinnes which haue beene the nayles and ſpeare, that haue tranſpierced thy bleſſed body. Thou who eſteemeſt thy ſins to bee but ſome indifferent or triviall thing; what deep paſſions of ſorrow ſhould thy heart and ſoule con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, to haue beene the cauſe of the death of thy friend, thy brother, thy father, or thy child, by <pb n="115" facs="tcp:173817:94"/>any action or accident of thine owne. But how much more grief &amp; ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row then oughteſt thou hereto retaine &amp; feele at the remembrance of thy ſins, which haue cauſed thy Creator to be mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, and thy God to be crucified to death.</p>
               <p>The II. Act of our hearts, which ought to ſtreame foorth and ariſe from that which the Lords bleſſed Supper expoſeth and preſenteth to our eyes, is the faith and aſſurance of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinnes. Thou ſayeſt to thy ſelfe, O <pb n="116" facs="tcp:173817:95"/>Sinner, I have offended God, and broken and tranſgreſſed his Law, therefore who ſhall ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and redeeme mee from his furious wrath and indignation: But be cheerefull and couragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, for loe here is thy ranſome, which Ieſus Chriſt brings and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth vnto thee in theſe words, <hi>This is my Body which hath beene bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for thee, This is my Blood that hath beene ſhed for thee,</hi> and wilt thou therefore doubt, when the only Sonne of God is hee who hath ſatisfied <pb n="117" facs="tcp:173817:95"/>for thee, and that it is not a ſilly man, but the eternall himſelfe, who is both thy righteouſnes and thy Redeemer; ſay then with the Apoſtle, <hi>who is hee, that will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne, ſith it is Chriſt that is dead:</hi> doſt thou doubt of Gods love, where his owne Sonne, the onely beloved of his Father, is the propitiation for thy ſinnes. If thou pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to thy ſelfe, thine owne merits, or the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of any other creatures or perſons, thou ſhouldeſt feare, that God will not receive <pb n="118" facs="tcp:173817:96"/>them for ſatisfaction, becauſe they are too baſe money, and of a falſe and counterfeit mettall, to be approved and received of God: But wee muſt preſent him, the body of his onely Sonne broken, and his blood ſhed, and then hee cannot, but ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove thereof as a full and valable ſatisfaction. God heeretofore knew the blood of the Lambe, vpon the poſtes of the doores, when he ſent his deſtroying Angell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Egypt;</hi> and will he not then know the blood
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:173817:96"/>of his owne Sonne, as of a Lambe without ſpot, or blemiſh, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by you have beſprinck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led your conſciences. Be therefore bold, and confident, and ſay with the Apoſtle to the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes,
<note place="margin">Hebr. 10.21,22.</note> 
                  <hi>Seeing wee have a high Prieſt, which is over the houſe of God, let vs draw neere, with a true heart in aſſurance of faith, our hearts being pure, from an evill conſcience,</hi> that ſo wee may obtaine mercy and find grace in due time: And here againe O faithfull Chriſtian, two reaſons of thy aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:173817:97"/>and confidence drawen from this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The one is, that as in Baptiſme, it is to thy ſelfe, to thine owne body, that the water is applyed; that thou may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thereby know, that thou art waſht in the blood of Ieſus Chriſt, ſo in this Sacrament of his bleſſed Supper; it is to thee that hee gives his body, yea it is into thine owne hands, which hee commits and puts this Sacrament, to aſſure thee, that it is onely to thee, which hee gives himſelfe, and not to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <pb n="121" facs="tcp:173817:97"/>whom thou may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt hold and eſteeme to be better then thy ſelfe: In which regard, for that this Sacrament is given to thee, and put into thine owne hands, it is becauſe thou muſt eſteeme, and beleeue, that Chriſts body is thine, as a Ranſome which is given into thy hands to preſent vnto God: wherefore doubt not, but it properly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs and appertaines vnto thee, for otherwiſe thou doeſt annull and annihilate the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which Chriſt giues
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:173817:98"/>thee, and thou doubteſt that he be true in giving it to thee.</p>
               <p>The other reaſon is, That although there hee a great diſtance betwixt Ieſus Chriſt &amp; vs, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Saint of Saints, and poore and miſerable ſinners; nevertheleſſe we learne by this Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that wee are incorpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with Chriſt, and into Chriſt, and that wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come his members, his blood, and his bone, as fleſh which wee eate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes our blood and bone. But to the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers and body, rightly
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:173817:98"/>belongs the power of the Head, which cannot bee denyed her. Thou mayeſt then inferre, O Chriſtian, that the righteouſneſſe of Ieſus Chriſt is thine owne, and that it properly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs and appertaines to thee.</p>
               <p>The third Act of our hearts in the participati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this Sacrament, is the ſanctifying of our ſoules, by the loue of God, and the denying and renouncing of our ſelues, the which is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by three things that are ſeene, &amp; appeare <pb n="124" facs="tcp:173817:99"/>in this Sacrament, that is to ſay:
<list>
                     <item>I. The great Charitie, and loue of God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards vs.</item>
                     <item>II. The foulenes and odiouſnes of ſinne.</item>
                     <item>III. The example of our owne dutie.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="1">I ſay firſt, The great charitie &amp; loue of God: For (my brethren) ſhould not this infinite love of God, in expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and delivering vp his onely begotten Son to death for vs, repleniſh, inſpire, and fill vs with a reciprocall love to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him; ſhould wee
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:173817:99"/>have ſuch ſtupid and ſenſeles hearts, that the Lords great compaſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on towards vs, ſhould nothing move, or ſtirre them vp; and ſuch fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen ſoules, that the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning charity of Ieſus Chriſt, dying for vs, could not heate and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame them in his love. Should wee wilfully of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend ſo great a goodnes in him, when we ſee, hee hath ſpared nothing for vs? Or is it poſſible, that ſo great (yea ſo extream) an ingratitude, hath poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed our hearts, and ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed our ſoules, as to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe <pb n="126" facs="tcp:173817:100"/>God, who hath loved vs ſo infinitely, as not to ſpare his onely Sonne for vs.</p>
               <p n="2">II. I ſpeak of the foul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and odiouſneſſe of ſinne, which appeares in this Croſſe: for ſhal we not hate ſinne, which is ſo diſpleaſing, and odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the eyes of our heavenly Father, that he would redeeme and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piate it with the death of his Son. Of a truth, if we repute &amp; eſteeme not <hi>Christs</hi> blood, for a light and triviall thing, needs muſt ſin bee very odious &amp; grievous vnto vs; and
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:173817:100"/>then needes muſt Ieſus Chriſt crucified, be vnto vs the powerfull motiue to crucifie the fleſh with the luſts thereof, and to mortifie in vs all, that which is of the old man, and of ſinne.</p>
               <p n="3">III. We haue the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of our dutie. In this Sacrament (O Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian) thou ſeeſt the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of the Sonne of God, which is a leſſon to teach thee to preſent thy body vnto God, as a living, holy and pleaſing ſacrifice. The patterne and modell of thy ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification, conſiſteth in <pb n="127" facs="tcp:173817:101"/>breaking, and chaſticing in thee the Old man, as thou ſeeſt the body of Chriſt broken on the Croſſe, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to dye vnto ſinne, as thou ſeeſt him dead. What, wilt thou now liue vnto that, for which Ieſus Chriſt dyed, and his fleſh which he cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied on the Croſſe, ſhall it againe reviue, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume life, and full and perfect vigour in thy members?
<note place="margin">Rom. 6 5.</note> Muſt thou not bee made the very ſame plant with Ieſus Chriſt, conformably to his death, to wit, that the <pb n="129" facs="tcp:173817:101"/>body of ſin be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in thee, to the end, that thou no more, nor no longer ſerue ſinne.</p>
               <p>But amongſt the parts of ſanctification, Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and loue towards our neighbours, is particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly requiſite and requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in this Sacrament, according to that of the Apoſtle:
<note place="margin">Iohn. 4.10,11.</note> 
                  <hi>Heerein is that loue, not that we loved God, but that hee loved vs, and ſent his Sonne to be a recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation for our ſinnes.</hi> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding likewiſe thereunto;
<hi>Beloved, if God ſo loued vs, we ought alſo to loue one the other.</hi> Wilt thou refuſe, <pb n="130" facs="tcp:173817:102"/>O Chriſtian, to loue and aſsiſt thy neighbour, for whom thou ſeeſt that Chriſt Ieſus refuſed not to ſhed his blood? Wilt thou refuſe to giue bread to him, to whom Ieſus Chriſt refuſed not his body? See therefore in this Sacrament, that which thou oweſt to thy neighbour, to wit, not onely to expoſe thy goods, but thy life for him; at leaſt, if thou thinke to haue any part in <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> according to that of Saint <hi>Iohn:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Iohn 3.16,17.</note> 
                  <hi>Heereby have wee percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved love, that hee layed <pb n="131" facs="tcp:173817:102"/>downe his life for vs, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee ought alſo, to lay downe our lives for our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren: and whoſoever hath the goods of this world, and ſeeth his brother have need, and ſhutteth vp his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſsion from him, how dwelleth the love of God in him;</hi> Thou therefore, who knoweſt not what it is, to give vnto the poore, and to comfort the afflicted; art thou not amazed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded in thy ſelfe, to conſider and behold, that Chriſt died for thoſe, with whoſe po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty and miſery thou <pb n="132" facs="tcp:173817:103"/>art ſo little (or rather no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all) moved or touched. Thou alſo who contemneſt thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, as thy inferiour, and vnworthy of thy company: behold how our Saviour Chriſt pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth him at the ſame ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble with thee, and nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheth him with the ſame meat, and gives him his owne Cup, as to thy ſelfe; and thou who liveſt in contention and diviſion, with thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, behold how Chriſt in this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment cals thee to the Communion of one and
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:173817:103"/>the ſame body, and will, that wee who are many, be one onely bread, and one onely body parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the ſame bread, as the Apoſtle ſpeakes to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Corint.
10.3.</note>.</p>
               <p>The fourth Act and duety, which muſt bee ingendered and propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated in our hearts by the meditation of this bleſſed Sacrament, is pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and conſolation in afflictions. Doſt thou ſee Gods Church per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted; <hi>It is the Body of Ieſus Chriſt, which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine broken, and his blood which is ſhed,</hi> that which <pb n="134" facs="tcp:173817:104"/>was the condition of this body on the Croſſe, and which is preſented to thee in this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the ſame is the condition of the myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call body on earth. What my brethren, doe wee ſo often ſee Chriſts body broken by the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, to bee after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſo ſtrangly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted and aſtoniſhed, to ſee the Church, which is the body of Chriſt, to ſuffer the like meaſure and fortune here on earth? Let vs therefore learne by this Sacrament,
<hi>That Ieſus <pb n="135" facs="tcp:173817:104"/>Chriſt crucified,</hi> is our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne here on earth, and that wee thereby know, that we are aſommoned and called to his Croſſe, and that wee are indeed his true body and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, if wee ſuffer with him, to the end, that we may likewiſe be glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with him; Say then all yee, who ſee this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament;
<note place="margin">Heb. 13.13</note> 
                  <hi>Let vs goe forth therefore to him out of the Campe, bearing his re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>proach.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Col. 1.24.</note> 
                  <hi>Let vs accompliſh and beare the ſufferings of Chriſt in our fleſh, for his bodies ſake, which is his Church, yea let vs every <pb n="136" facs="tcp:173817:105"/>where,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Corint 4.10.</note> 
                  <hi>beare about in our bodies, the death of Ieſus Chriſt, and that the life of our Lord Chriſt, may bee manifeſted in our mortall bodies:</hi> and all in general, let vs comfort our ſelues in our afflictions; and preſent and figure this beleife to our hearts and minds, that they come not from God, who pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth our ſinnes in his wrath and indignation; ſith this Sacrament teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth, that thoſe puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and revenges have alighted and fallen on Ieſus Chriſt himſelf, when his body was bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, <pb n="137" facs="tcp:173817:105"/>and his blood ſhed and ſpilt on the Croſſe; but they proceed ſimply from God, chaſticing, correcting, approving, and teaching vs as a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.32.</note> 
                  <hi>that wee bee not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned with the world;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hebr. 12.10.</note> 
                  <hi>that here below, being made Partakers of his holyneſſe;</hi> wee may hereafter in heaven bee made Parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of his felicity and glory.</p>
               <p>The fifth Function, which the bleſſed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſhould produce in vs, is, our hope of heavenly felicitie, according as <pb n="138" facs="tcp:173817:106"/>
                  <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> himſelfe ſaid to his diſciples, at the celebration of this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament,
<note place="margin">Mat. 26.29</note> 
                  <hi>I will drinke no more of the fruit of the vine, vntill that day that I ſhall drinke it new with you, in my Fathers King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome:</hi> by which words <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> will now raiſe, and elevate our hearts from the feaſt, which he makes vs here below in his favour, to that which he will here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after make vs above in his glory: and whereof he feaſt (or banquet) which he makes vs here on earth, in his Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <pb n="139" facs="tcp:173817:106"/>gives vs the firſt taſtes and reliſhes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the peace and ioy of conſcience, and the refreſhing and repleniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſoule in God, is a true beginning, and a ſhining ray of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights and felicities of heaven: wherfore faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Chriſtian, reioyce thou at theſe begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, in hope of that happy &amp; heavenly acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliſhment, which is pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſed thee, and through the eyes of thy faith, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold cheerefully and ioyfully, the tree of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life, which is in
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:173817:107"/>the <hi>Paradice</hi> of God, and the hidden
<hi>Manna</hi> (the bread of Angels) which thy Lord and Saviour prepares for thee: and behold the fulneſſe and ſatiety, which is prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for thee, in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred and glorious face of God, whereof <hi>David</hi> (in the times of the thickeſt, and obſcureſt ſhaddowes) ſaid,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 16.11</note> 
                  <hi>In thy preſence, O Lord, is fulneſſe of ioy, and at thy right hand are pleaſures for evermore.</hi> And againe in another place,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 65.4.</note> 
                  <hi>O how bleſſed is hee whom thou chooſeſt, and cauſeſt to come vnto thee,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:173817:107"/>he ſhall dwell in thy courts, and ſhall bee ſatisfied with the pleaſures of thine houſe and of thine holy Temple:</hi> and likewiſe in another,
<note place="margin">Pſal 36.8</note> 
                  <hi>They ſhall bee ſatisfied with the fatneſſe of thine houſe, and thou ſhalt give them drinke out of the River of thy pleaſures.</hi> Contemne, therefore <hi>(O Chriſtian)</hi> all earthly pleaſures in Compariſon of thoſe heavenly delights which paſſe all vnderſtanding; becauſe by this bleſſed Sacrament thou art in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uited and called to the wedding banquet of the Lambe, where thou <pb n="142" facs="tcp:173817:108"/>halt ſit downe with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Iacob,</hi> and where thou ſhalt be ſatisfied, and raviſhed with God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <p>And theſe (my belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed brethren) are the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations and functions, which God requires of vs, condignely and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily to receiue the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Sacrament of the Lords Supper, and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine vs religiouſly &amp; piouſly in the expecta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his comming; as this Sacrament was purpoſly inſtituted, to declare and foretell vs his death, and the ineſtimable benefits
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:173817:108"/>which iſſue and proceed thereof vnto vs, vntill he come. Let vs therefore examine and prooue our ſelues, if wee are of this holy diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for feare leſt eating this Bread, or drinking this Wine vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily, wee thereby make our ſelues guiltie of the Lords body and blood, and conſequently eat and drinke our owne damnation: And if wee find not this holy &amp; ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified diſpoſition in our hearts; let vs then effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually endeavor to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce &amp; enkindle it in vs, by the often reading and <pb n="144" facs="tcp:173817:109"/>meditating of the ſacred Bible, (the divine Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles) and written Word of God; as alſo by fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent &amp; inceſſant Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. For this Word of God (I ſay) is the Loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king glaſſe, wherin ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beholding the glorie of the Lord face to face,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.18.</note> 
                  <hi>wee are transformed and changed into the ſame I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage from glory to glory,</hi> as ſaith the Apoſtle. I ſay likewiſe, by Prayer, becauſe the Lord moſt benignly, and graciouſly conferres, and giues wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to all thoſe who ſeeke it of him, and hath <pb n="145" facs="tcp:173817:109"/>promiſed his holy ſpirit to all thoſe, who with humble &amp; contrit hearts demand it of him. And let vs poſſeſſe and retain this conſolation amidſt the defects and imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions which we feele in our hearts; that if we are diſcontented or ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, if we are afflicted &amp; heavie laden, that yet notwithſtanding, Chriſt wil not reiect vs, becauſe he ſaith, <hi>Come vnto me, all yee that are heavie laden:</hi> Or if we hunger &amp; thirſt after righteouſneſſe, (for this hunger and thirſt is a deſire of Gods grace, <pb n="146" facs="tcp:173817:110"/>proceeding from a liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſenſible feeling of our ſinnes) he promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to repleniſh and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie vs. May it there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore pleaſe thee, O our bleſſed Lord and Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, to call vs to this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Banquet, to ſend vs thy holy Spirit, and giue decent and religious diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions; and becauſe hee now knockes at the doore of our hearts by his holy Word, giue vs grace, that we may open it vnto him in the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of our faith, to the end
<note place="margin">Revel 3.</note> 
                  <hi>that hee may ſup with vs, and we with him;</hi> and <pb n="147" facs="tcp:173817:110"/>that he himſelfe may be both our Hoaſt, and our Banquet.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>A Prayer, to prepare our ſelues, before we receiue the holy Supper of the Lord.</head>
            <p>O God, how ſhall I preſent my ſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee, being a wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched creature, defiled &amp; polluted with ſin; If the Angels (who haue never ſinned) overvaile and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their faces, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they appeare before thy holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, <pb n="148" facs="tcp:173817:111"/>how much greater ought my aſtoniſhment and confuſion bee, who am guiltie of ſo many foule faults &amp; tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and likewiſe my griefe and ſorrow, ſith thy wrath reveales it ſelf from heaven againſt ſin, and that on every ſide we ſee the effects therof. Nature is afflicted and troubled, and our bodies are already poſſeſſed of diſeaſes and death, and therfore what greater pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment may our ſoules attend and expect; and if in this life thy wrath and indignation be thus <pb n="149" facs="tcp:173817:111"/>manifeſted, what will it be when we ſhal appeare before thy Tribunal; and that thou pronounce a ſharp and heavie ſentence againſt vs: but O Lord in this feareful amazement, here ariſeth vp to vs newes of grace, and mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of comfort and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation. Thou haſt had compaſſion of mankind, thou haſt ſent thine on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Son here below to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile and expiate our ſinnes; the earth had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for the ſaluation of man, the Angels who have no part of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, or of life, but <pb n="150" facs="tcp:173817:112"/>for themſelues could not reſiſt thine anger, but in ſtooping and ſincking downe vnder the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then therof. But O Lord thou haſt opened thine owne boſome, from whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce alone could come ſaluation; and from it thou haſt ſent thine only Sonne to cloth himſelfe with our nature, and to ſuffer therein the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment due to our ſinnes, and fully to ſatisfie thy Iuſtice for all our trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, ſo that we haue redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by his blood (to wit) remiſſion of ſins, according to the riches <pb n="151" facs="tcp:173817:112"/>and treaſure of thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; and we heare this thy Son to pronounce theſe ſweet &amp; pleaſing words in his Goſpel, <hi>Come to me all ye that are oppreſſed and heauy laden, and I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh and comfort you.</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verloaden then as I am, with the heavie burthen of my ſinnes, I come to diſcharge &amp; disburthen them on thy croſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath borne our ſinnes in his body on the wood therof And wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhould not I fully beleeue it, ſith this ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne loue, &amp; immenſe goodnes was worthy of <pb n="152" facs="tcp:173817:113"/>thee, and that not onely by thy Teſtament, but alſo by this Sacrament of thy bleſſed Supper, thou giveſt mee this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, and placeſt it (as it were) before mine eyes: For wherfore ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth this great Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but to repreſent to my ſoule, by faith, this great ſacrifice of Chriſts body, which he hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven &amp; preſented thee on the Croſſe. So becauſe I ſee my ranſome and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, have I not therefore iuſt cauſe, O my God, to reioyce and comfort my ſelf in thee, <pb n="153" facs="tcp:173817:113"/>that ranſome (I ſay) which thine owne ſelfe haſt freely given me. A divine ranſom, of a moſt ineſtimable price and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, becauſe it is the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of thine only begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Son, true God toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with thee. Heere, heere, O my God, it is, where my ſoule, (hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gring and thirſting after thy favour) finds where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall to freed &amp; refreſh her ſelfe. This body cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, is my true reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie; and this blood ſpilt and ſhed on the croſſe, is the liquor, wherwith my ſoule fills her ſelfe with <pb n="154" facs="tcp:173817:114"/>vnſpeakeable joy. And heere it is, where thy goodneſſe is ſo great, ſo infinite to all mankind, that thou inviteſt all thoſe who are hungrie and thirſty; Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe ſaying, <hi>Happie are thoſe who hunger and thirſt after righteouſneſſe, for they ſhall bee ſatisfied.</hi> O then, let my ſoule, which hungreth &amp; thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth after righteouſnes, (to wit, that righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, wherewith thou abſolveſt, and iuſtifieſt Sinners) obtaine the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and refreſhing of eternall life and ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <pb n="155" facs="tcp:173817:114"/>Then depart and flie hence from mee, all my doubts and diffidences, I will confirme and ſeale it, that God is true, in beleeving in his Sonne. For, ſhal I offer him this iniury, to doubt that he is good enough to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don my ſinnes, and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull enough to haue compaſſion of my miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries? If I behold, or looke vp to his Iuſtice, I am ſure that is appeaſed, and ſatisfied, becauſe <hi>Christ is hee, who dyed for mee,</hi> and I cannot doubt, that this death ſhall bee obiected or approoved <pb n="156" facs="tcp:173817:115"/>againſt me; becauſe Ieſus Chriſt became pledge, &amp; defender of all thoſe, who with repentant and contrite hearts, had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to him. To who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therefore ſhall I run, or flie, but to him, and why ſhall I not repent me, to haue offended thee, in that thou art ſo gracious &amp; mercifull towards vs, and that I ſee ſinne is ſo execrable, that onely thine owne Son muſt of neceſſitie die to expiate it; And if my repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance bee defectiue, and my faith infirme and weake, I will repreſent
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:173817:115"/>and ſhew thee that which thou thy ſelfe haſt ſayd, <hi>That thou wilt not breake the bruiſed reed, nor quench the ſmoking flax;</hi> &amp; I will ſay as he did in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, <hi>I beleeue, therefore O Lord, helpe my vnbeliefe.</hi> It is not for my repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and faith to giue, but to receiue ſaluation, the which is already purchaſed and deſerved by thy Son <hi>Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> Wee refuſe not a rich gift, either from a poore perſon, or a trembling hand: therfore, O Lord, I reioyce and comfort my ſelfe in this, that I <pb n="158" facs="tcp:173817:116"/>am diſpleaſed with mine owne ſins and tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and am truly ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull, and infinitly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentant, that I can repent them no more. O good God, were I free &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt of ſin, I the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> needed not this Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t which thou giveſt mee, for that it is a remedy againſt ſin, &amp; that thou doſt conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually invite vs to think and meditate with our ſelues how odious ſin is, and ought to bee to vs, becauſe of the filthie luſts, and pernicious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations, which reſide &amp; dwel in our members:
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:173817:116"/>for in heaven, where we ſhall ſinne no more, this remedy is needleſſe; Be mercifull therefore vnto mee, O God, becauſe of thy loving kindnes, and according to the infinit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of thy compaſſion, deface and doe away my tranſgreſſions: for I know that my ſinnes are ever before me. O God create in mee a pure heart, and reviue and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new in me thy holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; Cleanſe &amp; waſh me, O Lord, in the blood of thy bleſſed Sonne; feed my ſoule, which ſeekes her nouriſhment and life <pb n="160" facs="tcp:173817:117"/>in him; and if I am vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of thy favours, yet refuſe not ſome crummes of mercy to him, who humbly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents himſelfe to thy Table; Denie not (O Lord) the effect of thy mercy to him, who la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and weepes vnder the heavy burthen of his owne ſinnes and miſery, and who is religiouſly and conſtantly reſolued, for ever to celebrate thy infinite mercy and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſions.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="161" facs="tcp:173817:117"/>
            <head>A Prayer of Thankſgiuing after our receiving of the bleſſed Sacrament of the Lords Supper.</head>
            <p>O Eternall God, Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminate more and more the eyes of my vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, that I may conceive and compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend what is the height, depth, length, &amp; bredth of thy love towards vs in Ieſus Chriſt; what depth, when thou haſt drawen vs from the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of death, by the death of thy Son; what height, when thou haſt rayſed and elevated vs
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:173817:118"/>for him and with him to Heaven; what length but the laſting eternitie (from age to age) of all felicity, which thou haſt prepared for vs; what bredth, but as farre as the Eaſt is diſtant from the Weſt; ſo farre thou haſt baniſhed &amp; ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted our ſinnes from vs; and that as many pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes and bleſſings, as thou haſt pronounced vnto vs, they are ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, <hi>yea, and Amens in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</hi> O God who cauſeſt mee to behold this thy ſo wonderfull a goodnes, and who right <pb n="163" facs="tcp:173817:118"/>now co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meſt from ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to the eyes of my ſoule, in the receiving of this bleſſed Sacrament. Giue me grace, O Lord, to meditate and contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate theron, till I am ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhed in a ſpirituall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſie, yea, vntill I am transformed into the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of this thine owne love; and that I become all love towards thee; that I live no longer to my ſelfe, but that thy <hi>Chriſt</hi> may live in mee, through the love of thy divine goodnes &amp; beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and that I may em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace and retaine no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:173817:119"/>deſires, but for thee, and for the Kingdome of Heaven, which thou haſt transferd and given mee by thy bleſſed Son <hi>Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> O let me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold Sinne no more, but with horror and deteſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, becauſe it is con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trary to thy eſſence and beeing, as alſo to the worke of my redempti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on, which thy bleſſed Sacrament hath now proffered and preſented vnto mee. I ſee (O God, that thy Son is dead for Sinne; and therfore ſhall I live who am the vildeſt of all Sinners. That thy <pb n="165" facs="tcp:173817:119"/>
               <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath beene cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to deſtroy Sin, and therefore ſhall I give it ſtrength and vigour, to live and raigne in mee. O then (my mercifull God) let mee no longer live to, or for, the things of this world, but that I may crucifie my fleſh with all the ſinfull luſts thereof, and that the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sacrament, which I came now from recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, may bee the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and pourtrait of my duety, and my continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all leſſon, tending and working to the true mortification of ſinne in
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:173817:120"/>mee, and that it may be bruſed and broken, and left without ſtrength or life, as was the bleſſed body of my Saviour
<hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt,</hi> who died on the Croſſe for mee; and that alſo conformably to his reſurrection, I may hencefoorth live a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall and heavenly life, ſtill ſeeking <hi>thoſe things which are above, and not thoſe which are below on earth.</hi> And indeed, O Lord, by this thy holy Sacrament I ſee that I am vnited &amp; incorpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to thy <hi>Son Chriſt;</hi> and that I am thereby made <pb n="167" facs="tcp:173817:120"/>fleſh of his fleſh, and bone of his bone, and beeing thus adioyned with him; muſt I not alſo be conioyned with him in the ſame functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and affections. Shall I diſhonour the body of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> by my ſinnes and filthineſſe, and ſhall I take away his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, to make them the members of the world, or of Sathan. O how carefull ought I to be of my actions and duety, ſith in this vnion I reape this conſolation: that the obedience of
<hi>Chriſt</hi> is imputed to mee, as if <pb n="168" facs="tcp:173817:121"/>I my ſelfe had ſatisfied his iuſtice, to wit, That I am now made one, and the ſelfe ſame body with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who hath fully payed and ſatisfied for mee. How deare ought this Communion to bee vnto mee, whereby my Soule enioyeth peace, and aſſurance, ſeeing the full remiſſion of my ſins, and my abſolute and free deliverance from Gods heauy curſe, and fierce wrath, and indignation, whereby I ſee, that <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> eſteemeth, and cheariſheth mee as his owne body; aſwell, to <pb n="169" facs="tcp:173817:121"/>preſerue mee from all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils; as to beſtow on me all good things, which are neceſſary for me, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as the Apoſtle ſayes on this ſame ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect. <hi>That no man ever hated his owne fleſh, but doth nouriſh and cheriſh it, as God doth his Church.</hi> So then let Sathan prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe all his power, and exerciſe all his malice againſt mee, I (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding) cannot but be more then a Conqueror over all things in this body of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> and that if this his Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion oblige and tye mee <pb n="170" facs="tcp:173817:122"/>to croſſes and afflictions (for here on earth I muſt thus beare the death and paſſion of our <hi>Lord Ieſus</hi>) yet it doth aſſure mee both of victory, and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph: for the Spirit of God, which conducts &amp; quickneth this myſticall body of
<hi>Chriſt</hi> in vs, is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitly greater then that of the world, &amp; the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion which I have with the Croſſe of my Saviour, is my direct &amp; true way to glory. O my God, who makeſt me to reliſh theſe delights of thy loue, and who in this maner feedeſt &amp; repleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheſt
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:173817:122"/>my ſoule at thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly table; Giue me grace, that he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceforth I may no more truſt the delights and pleaſures of ſin. Let my deſires &amp; delights be to obey and do thy will, and that all the whole courſe &amp; progreſs of my life, may bee a ſanctified preparation to this great wedding banket of the <hi>Lambe,</hi> wherunto we are invited &amp; called, &amp; wher thy holy &amp; ſacred ſight wilbe vnto vs a fulnes of all ioy, &amp; thy right hand an vnſpeakable delight, &amp; pleaſure for evermore. Let me then (O Lord) at <pb n="147" facs="tcp:173817:123"/>this very inſtant, clothe my ſelfe with the wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding garment of thy ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification, therewith to bee preſent at this Feaſt, whereof this of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, (wherunto thou haſt now invited mee) is an earneſt &amp; pledge; and that ſeparating my ſelfe from the people of this world, (whoſe only por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is in this preſent life) I may ſay with the royal Prophet <hi>Dauid, As for me (O Lord) I ſhall ſee thy face in righteouſnes, and I ſhall be filled with thy image and reſemblance, when I ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:173817:123"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
